<topics>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-19th-amendment/selected-articles</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85058130/1890-03-27/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	      <rel>1</rel>
	      <text> Discussing Wyomings Admission
WASHINGTON MarclT28 Tho committee on
rules reported a resolution making tho Wyom
ing admission bill the special order for today
recess to be taken at 530 this afternoon until 11
oclock tomorrow the previous question to be
considered ordered at 1 oclock Adopted and
the Wyoming bill taken up
Baker of New York submitted an argument
I favor of the measure
Barnest of New York opposed the bill be
cause he believed there were gross irregulari
ties in the adoption of the constitution of
Wyoming because hebelloved the territory did
not contain the population requisite and be
cause there were incorporated in the constitu
tion features based upon the subject of female
suffraEO antagonistic to republican institutions
Carey of Wyoming made a strong plea for
the admission of the territory He contended
that its constitution was adopted by the free
and fair vote of its citizens and its population
was sufficient Ho defended the provision of
the constitution extending the right of suflrage
to women He said that President Harrison
had endeared himself to the people of Wyoming
by observing the spirit of the Republican na
tional platform respecting the appointment of
territorial residents to territorial offices and
with more manhood than his predecessor say
ing no to eastern office seekers Neither politi
cal party could make a point by obstructing the
admission of Wyoming She had people she
observed the laws she had no factional quar
rels Wyoming young and enterprising would
hasten to overtake tno older states and help
them bear the burdens of government
Crocker of Missouri opposed the bill I was
nothing more nor less than n partisan measure
designed to perpetuate tho power of the Repub
lican party It like the Idaho bill should
be called a bill to add three electoral votes and
two Senators to the Republican column in 1892
Oates of Alabama opposed the measure be
cause it proposed to give women the right to
vote and made attendance at school com
pulsary
Dunncll of Minnesota was inclined to vote
against the bill on account of the woman suffrage
clause
Washington of Tennessee attacked tho
womans suffrage clause and held the people of
Wyoming had violated the provision of the act
of organization limiting the suffrage to white
male suffrage Women might be sent from
Wyoming to the Senate
E B Taylor of Ohio Dont you think that to
put good women Into the Senate might help it
some Laughter
Washington the gentleman himself were
In the Senate I might admit his proposition
Kerr of Iowa thought the opponents the
bill in bad straits whon they fell back for objec
tion upon the womans suffrage provision
Kelly of Kansas said he would not be
frightened i women had a seat on the floor of
the House and perhaps it would result in
benefit
Morey of Ohio favored the bill and advo
cated the civil and legal enfranchisement of
women In all the states of the union After fur
ther debate the House took a recess until 11
oclock tomorrow
Bills for the erection of public buildings to
day were reported to the Houso by the commit
tee on public buildings as follows Spokane
Falls Washington site for building IOJ000 I
Stockton Cal 70000 Helena Mont 125000
    </text>
    </result>
    <result>
	    <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85066387/1895-05-21/ed-1/seq-4/</id>
	    <rel>1</rel>
	    <text>WOMAN`S CONGRESS 1895
The second annual session of the
Woman's Congress of the Pacific Coast
was called to order in Golden Gate Hall
yesterday morning at 10:30 o'clock by the
president, Mrs. Sarah B. Cooper of tnis
City. Before it had concluded its first
day's labors, the home, the new woman,
motherhood and child training, and that
universally interesting subject, marriage,
were handled vigorously— the latter, in
several instances, without gloves.
The beautifully decorated hall was filled
to overflowing for quite a time before the
hour announced for the opening. Every
seat in the auditorium was taken, the gal
leries were packed and jammed with fair
women and their escorts, and the aisles be
low were crowded with many ladies and
quite a number of men — brave men at that
to venture into such a maze of feminine
loveliness, wit and wisdom.
The ladies of the auxiliary had worked
hard to make the big bare stage look pic
turesque, and their efforts were crowned
with complete success. The walls sur
rounding the platform were covered by
tall, slender bamboo trees, which were in
terspersed with a few good prints and en
gravings. Handsome screens and shaded
lamps helped to give the stage a drawing
room effect, which was completed with
pretty chairs and lounges.
The president's table was a mass of fra
grant crimson roses, in the midst of which
was placed a marble statuette of the fa
mous Lucretia Mott. Susan ±5. Anthony's
seat had been made almost as gorgeous as
a regal throne. It was an antique, high
backed chair, which the ladies had dsaped
with old gold plush and wreathed with
yellow marguerites, tied with orange rib
bons — the suffrage color.
Flowers were everywhere on the plat
form. Suspended from the ceiling,
"Woman's Congress, 1895." could be read
in large floral letters, and the left side of
the platform was entirely banked up with
an immense floral tribute which an anony
mous friend had sent to the president.
. Ana Susan B. Anthony herself, the
grand old woman of woman's rights, the
evangel of the new woman, as new as she
beamed upon the welcoming faces before
her as the newest woman of them all.
White handkerchiefs waved and hands
clapped at her initial appearance, and her
utterances throughout the day were em
phatically punctuated by the warmest
demonstrations. The Rev. Dr. Anna H.
Shaw, the first lieutenant of Miss Anthony,
received her full 6hare of the plaudits of
the audience. Her utterances were mer
rily pointed shafts at many things, none
the lesE telling for their humor, and served
only to strengthen the impression the peo
ple had gained of the reverend spinster
through the prints of the country.
And the women of California. They, too,
did themselves and their State proud by
their efforts on the rostrum. The address
of Mrs. Sarah B. Cooper, the president,
was one of the most beautiful, direct and
logical ever delivered from any platform
in San Francisco, barring none. It evoked
the warmest applause from the visitors
and fairly took the congress by storm. It
was epigrammatic and instructive, sound
and witty, *he extemporaneous interpola
tions being particularly fetching.
Miss Kelso of Los Angeles took occasion
to come to gentle issues with 'if iss An
thony during the afternoon on the ques
tion of "marriage bondage," and did so in
a manner that most certainly has won her
the hearts of those newly married and who
expect to be newly married, at least.
Miss Millecent Shinn and Miss Anna
Stovall of this city also read papers which
covered them with honor.
The congress will convene again at 10
o'clock this morning, when a business
meeting will be held and officers elected
for the ensuing year.
VIEWED BY A WOMAN.
Miriam Mlchelson Clves Her Im-
pression of the Con
gress.
When I stepped into a Suiter-street car
Monday morning there was a woman
seated in the corner opposite me. Her
hair was a faded, grayish red, her face was
lined and rather colorless, and her promi
nent pale blue eyes were tearful and mel
ancholy. But she was really more mind
less than miserable, and her sorrowful
appearance, it seemed to me, was due
more to weakness than to woe. More
women entered the car on its way down
town, a mother with her two daughters, a
gray-haired woman and others. Their
faces were just the ordinary, preoccupied
faces of women who haven't much time or
wish for thought or action other than the
duties which are typically feminine.
At Larkin street a crowd of women came
in. They were on • their way to the
Women's Congress. You would have
known it by the important-looking little
documents they carried, by the fuss and
flutter of their conversation, by the de
mure, business-like style of their clothes,
but most of all by an awakened sexless
intelligence in their faces and the self-con
fidence in their brisk movements. The
women already in the car looked them
over from toe to bonnet; then their faces
subsided into indifference and self-absorp
tion—all but the woman in the corner.
She seemed fascinated by the new woman.
She stared at her, she knit her light brows
feebly, and positively forgot her troubles
in watching this new kind of female.
When the car stopped at the corner and
with a bustling dignity the new woman
alighted, suddenly the old woman rose too
in a dazed, uncertain way and followed
the crowd. She passed into the hall and
I lost sight of her.
Women, women ! All kinds and degrees
of women. They filled hall and balcony;
they stood against the walls, and, stand
ing, filled the aisles. They were enthu
siastic and hopeful and full of excitement.
"I do hope they'll begin on time. Women
never do, you know," said an excitable,
well-dressed young matron.
"Perhaps they're waiting for some man.
A man's name is first on the programme —
or rather program," chuckled a bright-
THE INAUGURATION OF THE WOMAN'S CONGRESS AT GOLDEN GATE HALL YESTERDAY MORNING.
{Sketched by a " Call" artist.]
faced woman with short dark hair streaked
with gray.
The other smiled appreciatively, then
she said, "Well, you know, punctuality
isn't one of woman's virtues."
"I don't know about that," said the
other stoutly. "I'm always on time and
so are you."
"Yes, but we both were business women.
Besides, you know, men make such fun of
us about that."
The short-haired woman sniffed rather
scornfully.
"This morning," she said, "coming over
on the boat there was just the homeliest
woman I ever saw. A regular fright. John
said, 'I bet she's going to the Woman's
Congress. 1 'I bet a nickel she isn't.' I said-
THE SAN FRANCISCO CALL, TUESDAY, MAY 21, 1895.
So we watched her, and when she got off
at Kearny street I collected my bet. But
I got more than a nickel's worth of satis- i
faction out of it."
There was triumph in every woman's
eye when half-past ten arrived, and with
it the president and principal members of
the congress. So much for man's accepted
ideas of woman. But although there is a
tendency in some of the speakers to at
tribute all the ills that flesh and morals
are heir to to the political slavery of
women, I heard nothing at all of "tyrant
man." On the contrary, a gentle, forbear
ing patience was manifest in most of the
allusions to him. He is unhappily in the
wrong, but that is his misfortune, not his
fault, and with time and feminine reme
dies they hope to enlighten and ultimately
to convert him. I discovered, too, that al
though the new woman insists upon shar
ing man's political and business life, she
intends that he shall be compensated by
increased responsibility as husband and
father.
"Every mother owes it to her child that
he be well-born," read an essayist yester
day.
"And so does every father," she added
in one of those significant asides, which
characterize women's speeches.
But the most striking thing about this
woman's convention is the spirit of com
raderie it fosters. At Golden Gate Hall
women are actually so interested in things
that they put aside forms. Introductions
are unnecessary. If you can tell your
neighbor that that shy, sunburned, dark
haired girl is Beatrice Harraden ; that this
woman with the intellectual oval face is
Charlotte Perkins Stetson, that that one
who wears her hair in a gray mane down
her back is Laura de Force Gordon ; that
the bust is of Lucretia Mott; if you know
which is Susan B. Anthony and the Eev.
Anna Shaw; if you know who is the
woman in the swell gown and the one that
looks like a guy, the woman next to you
will not hesitate to make use of you. I
saw a young woman rise and offer her
chair in a very gentlemanly manner to an
older woman she did not know, saying
simply, "I should have liked to give you a
seat before, but the crowd is 8O great I
couldn't get out."
These congress women seem to have lost
some feminine vices and gained some mas
culine virtues. Their self-possession is not
the assertive arrogance of small-minded,
notoriety-seeking females. Their convic-
tion is tempered with dignity and charity.
Tney are not shrewish, and they deliver
their message in a frank, good-natured
way. They have learned how to disagree
without quarreling, and they are willing
to admit that there are two sides to a ques
tion and an infinite number of points of
view. I don't know that this makes them
more admirable to men, but it makes
them more women's women. The audi
ence yesterday certainly showed great en
thusiasm ; they indulged in that feminine
kind of applause known astheChautauqua
salute, and the speakers were quite old
womanly in their allusions to "Dear Aunt
Susan," "Saint Susan B. Anthony," "That
martyr, Lucretia Mott," and "Our dear
Elizabeth Cady Stanton." But there is an
accent of sincerity and evidence of un
usual friendship among women in the ac
counts of those old days "when our ideas
were not received with applause, nor our
selves overwhelmed with flowers," as Miss
Anthony gently expresses it.
The congress woman is evidently deeply
religious. "Orthodox of the orthodox,"
said Rey. Anna Shaw. Miss Shaw tells a
story well. She is the most manly, not
mannisn, woman in the congress. Her
voice is deep and full. She speaks clearly
and can be heard all over the hall. She
tells with a chuckle of Miss Anthony's
wish to impress an Eastern audience with
the propriety of their religious views, and
of the unfortunate figure of speech she
used- when she introduced Miss Shaw as
her "right bower." "But," gleefully adds
the Rev. Anna Shaw, "every man in that
orthodox community knew what a right
bower is."
"The religion," said Mrs. Cooper in her
opening address, "which is all for the next
world and none for this, is good for
neither."
"Amen to that!" came in hysterical,
quavering tones from the back part of the
hall.
Everybody turned around. It was the
Old Woman with the faded red hair, who
had sat in the corner of the car. Her pale
eyes were bright with excitement, there
were two red spots on her high cheek
bones, and her hat was a little awry. But
she was quite unconscious of people's at
tention. The chair upon which she sat
had been to her a penitent's bench, she
had suddenly come to a realization of new
womanhood, and when the next speaker
said in tones of conviction: "The new
woman has come to stay," another heart
felt "Amen!" from theback of the hall
attested the Old Woman's conversion.
Miriam Michelson.
THE MORNING SESSION.
Miss Susan B. Anthony and Rev.
Anna Shaw Receive
Ovations.
The opening session of tbe congress was
brought to order rather informally by the
appearance on the stage about 10:30 o'clock
of the president, Mrs. Sarah B. Cooper,
leading the way for Miss Susan B. Anthony
and the Rev. Dr. Anna H. Shaw. No
sooner did the vast audience catch sight of
these ladies than it broke out into the
wildest kind of applause, most of the ladies
rising to their feet and waving their hand
kerchiefs in salute. The pioneer in the
movement for female suffrage, spectacled
and white-haired as she was, was bright
eyed ana active, and as she took the deco
rated seat set apart for her she beamed on
the happy faces before her.
Mrs. Cooper wasted no time in the pre
liminaries, and as the afficers of the con
gress took their seats on the platform she
rapped for order.
"Friends and co-workers," sne said, "I
see before me a great many faces that
greeted us a year ago, and we welcome
you, thrice welcome you, this morning.
'The blessing of God maketh rich, and it
hath no sorrow. 1 And we are to have the
j invocation for his presence and his blessing
by the Rev. Dr. Brown."
The eloquent pastor of the First Congre
gational Church delivered a solemn prayer
for the right guidance of the convention,
the audience listening reverentially and
attentively till the final amen.
"His Excellency the Governor," said
Mrs. Cooper again, addressing the con
gress, "is, no doubt, attending the funeral
services of our venerated first Governor,
Peter H. Burnett. Hence, we shall be
disappointed in not having the welcome
of his Excellency. But we shall not be
disappointed in having the welcome of tne
Hon. Mayor Sutro. I introduce to you
Mayor Sutro."
There was more applause as the
monarch of the cliffs rose and bowed to
the storm ol greeting. He said :
Ladies: The pleasant duty and honor de-
TuJ? H2 on me to welcome you to the City of
the Golden Gate— an honor in this case doubly
appreciated, as I see assembled in this hall
women from different parts of the United
States who have spent their lives in devotion
to the betterment of the human family.
The aristocracy of European countries dates
back to the dark ages, when Kings and Queens
often made noblemen of free lances who had
shown the greatest prowess and skill in war
if • or the P ur P°se of utilizing their talent to
add strength and support to the throne.
Here in America we have allowed to be
reared an aristocracy of money — our railway
magnates, men who have accumulated enor
mous fortunes by chicanery and oppression,
and by evil means corrupted our Government,
which is now domineered over by great cor
porations.
We ought to strive and develop in this coun
try a different kind of aristocracy, that of
the brain, of worth, of Intelligence and of ad
vancement.
If we take that standard we shall find gath
ered in this hall a higher aristocracy than ever
assembled in any hall in the king-ridden coun
tries of Europe.
The participation of women (the mothers of
our coming generations ot men) in the selec
tion of those who are to govern the country
will elevate the Nation and give a higher
standard to political affairs.
AVomen are endowed by nature with a finer
quality of brain power ; they have a sort of in
tuitive knowledge of character and are gener
ally correct in their judgment.
I believe in evolution; I think It a part of
evolution that women, who thus far, in the
history of the world, have been denied a share
in the affairs of government, should be per
mitted to cast their ballots in favor of a puri
fied and improved administration which will
cause us to rise higher and higher in civillza-
Nothing could well be worse than our pres
ent status; political bosses, corruptly hand
ling the money-sacks of corporations, rule and
debase our great country.
Let noble women step in and restore the
honesty, simplicity and patriotism of the revo
lutionary fathers and all will be well.
I see in this hall one woman (Miss Anthony)
whom more than a quarter of a century ago I
have seen, year after year, struggling with
Senators and Representatives at Washington
to obtain the political rights of women, and
who has persistently since and continuously
fought the battle of freedom, and I wish espe
cially to do her honor and welcome her and
welcome you all, and hope that you will carry
to your homes kind and lasting recollections
of your assembly in this Cty by the Golden
Gate.
"I have the very great honor, now," said
Mrs. Cqoper, stepping to the front of the
platform and grasping the hand of Miss
Anthony, "of introducing to this large
assemblage one who I believe has done more
to lift up womanhood, to lift up humanity,
than any other living woman. This
I firmly believe. I have the pleasure of in
troducing Miss Susan B. Anthony, who
will respond to the Mayor's address of wel
come."
Loud handclappings almost drowned the
last words of the ' president, and as Miss
Anthony advanced the vast audience arose
as one person and wildly waved handker
chiefs in the Chautauqua salute to the
white-haired grand old woman of the rights
of woman.
"Mrs. President, Mr. Mayor and friends,"
said Miss Anthony, as soon as the wave
of enthusiasm had passed, "it is but a few
minutes over twenty-four hours since my
friend, Miss Shaw, and myself stepped foot
on California soil, and this is the third
vast congregation of your California peo
ple which we have met— the third vast
audience — and the welcome which your
Mayor has extended, the welcome which
these vast assemblages of the men and
women of your City and your Brooklyn
across the water— for while lam here I
can only think of New York and Brooklyn
to be compared with Ran Francisco and
Oakland— do not fail of appreciation from
me. Certainly any heart that could fail to
appreciate such an ovation— such a recog
nition—would be wanting in the common
est elements of human nature.
"lam grateful for this welcome, not
from any personal consideration. While
that is flattering enough, I can assure you
I take it for the cause for which you make
the recognition. lam no better looking;
I, personally, have no more brain, nor
more power of statement than I had forty
years ago — and, forty years ago, whenever
my friends, Elizabeth Cady Stanton and
the venerated and sainted Lucretia Mott,
whenever any of us went into a commun
ity, the whole community did not take off
their hats in reverent recognition of our
coming, but, on the other hand, it was
with hootings and with jeers and with
words that were not complimentary they
met us.
"It is because the world is coming, not
to admire the exterior of Lucretia Mott,
the exterior of Elizabeth Cady Stanton, or
any of the advocates of this great move
ment that this ovation comes. It is be
cause the idea which these women pro
mulgated almost half a century ago has
become acceptable to the people, and not
only acceptable, but it has become the
cornerstone of the faith in our republic, of
the faith in our Christianity and of the
faith in our country altogether. There
fore, whatever of courtesy, whatever of
congratulation you offer to my friend, Miss
Shaw and myself, who have come across
the mountains and the plains in order to
look you in your faces in the great con
gregation — whatever you tender to us,
seemingly personal, she and I and all
of the friends who are not able to be here
to-day-^-Mrs. Stanton, the one survivor of
the women who called the first conventiou
that was ever held of women in 1848, she,
sitting in her little room in her little home
in the city of New York, will feel to-day
this ovation, this congratulation, this ora
tion, quite as much as we who are here.
And everywhere where woman has awak
ened to her new destiny, to her new hope,
to her new realization, everywhere where
woman has thus awakened all over the
face of this globe, will go the Associated
Press dispatches of this tender of recogni
tion and respect and reverence for the
women who first promolgated this grand
idea of perfect equality of rights, civil,
religious, social, literary, educational, for
the women of the world."
Loud hand-clappings interrupted the
flow of eloquence from the lips of Miss
Antnony, and the waving handkerchiefs
in the crowded seats, the packed aisles and
the jammed galleries, looked like myriad
mammoth flakes of purest snow falling
from the canopy above.
"I am glad to be here," resumed Miss
Anthony, smiling at the smiling audience
before her. "You will remember, some of
you who are old enough to remember, that
this is not my first visit to your coast. It
will be twenty-four years ago, when the
11th day of June shall have come, since
Mrs. Stanton and myself first arrived in
your City.
"We are not without recognition then;
we were not without a most cordial recep
tion then, but it was not by the multitude
as it is now. It was the few. I remember
that when Mrs. Stanton appeared before
the vast audience, Mr. Stanford, the then
Governor of the State, made the formal ad
dress of welcome and presided at the meet
ing, and Mis. Stanford and himself ten
dered every possible compliment to us as
their guests at the Grand Hotel, which
was then new and magnificent.
"We have had grand California repre
sentatives in the East from the beginning.
As I began wending my way back by the
railroad on that trip, having just finished
speaking at Virginia City and gone down
to Reno to take the train, I found there
was not a single berth to be had. All were
taken. Your men had then elected as
Senator of the United States, the Hon. A.
A. Sargent. He and his family were then
on board that train, and, very kindly, the
two daughters of Senator Sargent shared
their stateroom with me, and I found"
resting place and ;; became thoroughly ac
quamted^with your Senator and Mrs. Sar
fhnir?^ f £° m u that d »y,to this 1 have had
fo h n°oTin ln s a h n S |SsS ether * "- I **
'-Then after Senator Sargent, you sent
friend* Who WaS OUr &d ™™** and
Khn nd then ' y< ? u sent Inland Stan
as thS £v a3> , all with his wife as well
bLt frt£} 6: of :; Senator •? Sargent, of our
best friends over on the other side of the
S Califn? 8 *- S0) while we have not
iwP» iforni W who live *in I New York
and Pennsylvania and Washington, we are
no strangers to the representatives of Cali-"
th«?-' * ud lam 'S l ad to stand here and say
rnnL^ a£S j knowledge of them ia
concerned they have been worthy of your
confidence. v . your
"Now, I will say again that I am glad to
be here, and I expect to get a good deal
more good out of this council of the women
of the Pacific Slope than it is possible for
you to get from nay being here with you."
Aerain the hall rang with applause and
the flower-scented air was agitated by the
waving of spotless handkerchiefs as the
honored pioneer who bad blazed the path
for the new woman, bowing to the right
and left, took her seat.
"There has been a call from the audi
ence," said Mrs. Cooper, advancing as the
applause subsided, "for one who captured
both Oakland and San Francisco yester
day. 1 have the honor of introducing the
Rev. Anna Shaw."
"I want to say to Mrs. Copper and to
this audience," exclaimed Miss Anthony,
rising before Miss Shaw had time to step
forward, "that Miss Anna Shaw is my
first lieutenant, and she is not only my
first lieutenant, but is the first lieutenant
of the great National Woman's Council of
the United States. She is vice-president
at large. She comes to you representing
that body, which is composed of twenty
of the different National organizations
of women of this country, representing
twenty different purposes of the women
who have been organized, and I hope be
fore this Pacific Council shall adjourn you
will vote yourselves members of that great
National organization of the women of
the United States."
More applause, and Mrs. Cooper again
introduced Miss Shaw, who came forward
smiling at the white greeting of waving
handkerchiefs.
'•My friends," she began, "ycu make me
feel bashful, because I come with Susan to
hold her bonnet, and it is honor enough
for any young woman to hold the bonnet
of Susan B. Anthony. But as you have
called me here, I am almost tempted to tell
a joke on her. Some time since, they toll
the women in this movement that the •
were out of their sphere. Finding that
this did not scare us, they said we were
strong-minded. Well, I would rather be
strong-minded than have no mind at all.
Then, when none of these things seemed
to have any effect on us, they called us a
lot of infidels, and that nearly scared us to
death. Here's where the joke comes in.
"One night in introducing me to a con
gregation in a large church Miss An
thony wanted to impress upon her
hearers that I at least was not an infidel.
'This is the Rev. Anna Shaw,' she said, 'an
orthodox minister. She is orthodox of
the orthodox, and she is my right bower.'
"Now just think of the "impression on
that congregation," resumed Miss Shaw,
when the laughter at her joke had ceased
echoing. "And the interesting thing
about it was that every orthodox person
in the congregation knew what a right
bower was.
"Gentlemen and ladies, I certainly thank
yon on behalf of the Women's Council,
which lam representing here ; and I thank
you on behalf of Miss Anthony, myself
and the other ladies who have gathered
from various parts of the country to bu
present at this congress. I thank you o:i
behalf of womanhood, because I think this
congress means better conditions for the
home and, if for the home, then for the
whole world. President Eliot of Harvard
says the home is the sap-root of the state,
and if that be bo, whatever tends to uplift
the state uplifts the home. There can be
no perfect state without a perfect home ;
and there can be no perfect state, if the
home is the sap-root of the state, without
direct connection between the sap-root and
the state.
"If you sever from the life of the state
one-half of the tap-root you sever one-hali
of the power and vital energies of the
state. That for which Miss Anthony and
Mrs. Stanton stand is the direct connec
tion between the tap-root and the state,
and we have come to see this great prin
ciple accepted all over our country by the
wisest and best people. We thank you for
your welcome to our ideas and to our
principles and, in the name of the
Women's Council, which I hope to speak
of hereafter, I thank you for this kindly
welcome."
"I now take pleasure," said the presi
dent, "in introducing to you Mrs. Caroline
M. Severance of Los Angeles, one of the
earliest of those women who stood for suf
frage, and, not only that, but the first
president of the New England : Women's
Club; 1 and if I were to tell all that Mrs.
Severance has done for the Pacific Coast I
should rob her of a good portion of her
time. It is my great pleasure and honor
to introduce to you, therefore, Mrs. Caro
line M. Severance of Los Angeles."
There was more waving of nandkerchiefs
as Severance took her stand to the
left of the president, at the rear of the
magnificent floral arch. Her voice trem
bled with emotion as she responded to the
reception and she was visibly affected. She
said she had neither strength nor voice
enough to tell bow grateful she was. Her
heart and her effort had always been with
the work at present in hand and her in
terest had never flagged since 1848. J
"Susan can tell, she concluded. "We
have been co-workers in a way." •
"Yes," said Miss Anthony, once more
rising, "let me tell you about Mrs. Sever
ance. Just forty-two years ago, in the
beautiful month of October, the third, or
fourth, or fifth meeting of the woman's
rights convention— we talked about the
woman's right to earn an honest living
and to get an education— just forty-two
years ago next October such a convention
was held in the city of Cleveland. I was a
guest of this dear woman at that time,
Lucy Stone, Antoinette Brown, dear
Lucretia Mott and Fannie Gage, as we
called her, Ernestine Rose of . New York a
Polish woman who said ■ such beautiful
things in broken English. I think we
were nearly all the guests of Mrs. Sever
ance. I remember that beautiful home of
hers out on Euclid avenue— a palace where
we used to love to assemble.
o "Ah, how different it was then, Mrs.
Severance," said Miss Anthony, turnine to
her old friend. "How different it was.
Instead of having a preacher to come and
pray for us, we actually had one take Mr
Garrison by the nose. Yes, Mrs. Sever
ance has been with us from : the , begin
ning." °
The Rev. Ada C. Bowles of Pomona
added her tribute to the work and worth
of Mrs. Severance, and called upon the
audience to give her the Chautauqua
salute, which was done with a will. The
president then introduced to the audience
the following ladies, who made short ad
dresses appropriate to the occasion: Mrs.
John F. Swift, president of the Century
Club of San Francisco; Mrs. I. Lowenbe'rg,
president of the Laurel Hall and Philo
math clubs; Miss Mary C. Smith of the
Ladies' Literary Society of Santa Maria;
Mrs. Nellie Blessing Eyster of the
Women's Press Association of the Pacific
Coast; Mrs. Eliza Orr, corresponding sec
retary of the Women's Council of Califor
nia, and Mrs. H. E. Brown of the State W.
C T. XJ .
Mrs. Ada Van Pelt then took the chair
and introduced to the audience the presi
dent, Mrs. Sarah B. Cooper, who was
greeted with much applause and the sight
of many fluttering handkerchiefs. She de
livered the following address:
Representative Women of the Nation and of the
Pacific Coast— Honored Friends: I thank Yon
for your cordial greeting.
    </text>
    </result>
    <result>
      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045211/1916-11-11/ed-1/seq-6/</id>
      <rel>1</rel>
      <text> WONDER-WOMAN" IS MISffJEANNETTE RANKIN;
WILL BE FIRST OP SEX TO SIT IN CONGRESS
"Analytic and Energet
ic" Characterization
of Suffrage Leader
Who Is Likely to Add
M. C. to Name
What America's First Woman
Congressman Stands Fpr
NATIONAL womnn suffrage.
Protection of childhood.
Stato nnd national prohibition.
Farm loan law.
Equal taxation.
By LISETTA NEUKOM
MODESTY marks tho expression of the
woman who Is America's first fcml
nlno "Congress oman," Miss Jeannette Han
kin, of MlHsoula, Mont., to whom returns
today give the seat In Congress from Mon
tana Although she defeated seven men In the
primaries for the placo by a plurality of
7000, nnd will receive J7B0O a year salary
when she takes her seat In Congress, but
gives all to the women of Montana.
1 nm going to Washington to represent
tho women and children of tho West to
work for nn eight-hour day for women nnd
for laws providing that women shall be paid
tho same wuges as men for equal amounts
of work."
Mlsi Ilankln, the newly elected Congress
woman, was sewing as she said this today,
according to a dispatch from Missoula,
liven after entering politics sho refused to
forsake tho old household arts, cooking and
needlowork Miss Knnkln failed to become
cxcltod when returns showed she was run
ning nhead of tho itepubllcan ticket In
Montana nnd later thnt sho was elected.
"I'm glad of this chance," was her com
ment when cheering friends "broke the
news."
"Of course," said Miss ltankln today, "I
know I'll bo tho first woman member of
Congress, but I won't bo tho last and I be
lieve I'll bo received with courtesy nnd as
nn equal by thoso Kastern Congressmen,
even though they nre enemies of suffrage.
Whllo working for suffrage In the Knst I
found that no matter how strenuously -our
opponents fought us, they wore always
ready to hear our sldo."
"This Is not my campaign," she says.
"The splendid vote I hove received In the
contest, ns well ns the hearty reception I
havo been given throughout tho State while
campaigning, Is simply n demonstration of
tho determination of Montana women to
havo a womnn represent their Interests In
Congress.
"Tho women are fighting for r. principle,
n new Iden In representation," she added,
"nnd they stood together behind my enn
dldacy becnuse they believe It means some
thing bigger than sending Jeannetto ltan
kln to Congress I nm surely grnteful to the
women for their loynl support nnd I deeply
appreciate the honor and tho responsibility
of their having chosen mo ns their candi
date "
STATU ritOl'D OF llKIt
Although Mlsn Itnnkln herself Is modest
about bor own achievements, women from
her native State. Montana, with whom I
have been in communication are not at all
modest for her They say In no uncertain
terms- that It Is the Indefatigable energy,
charming personality and wonderful work
sho has accomplished for tho women of
Montana that have given her tho well
earned honor of being selected as the first
MISS JEANNETTE RANKIN
HOW TO GUARD
YOUR BEAUTY
'GAINST THE WINDS
By LUCREZIA BORI
rrlma Donna nf th Metropolitan Oner.
Company. '
woman In the United States to go to Con
gress. Miss Uelle Fllgclman, of Helena, Mont.,
herself a staunch worker In the cause ot
women and suffrage, tells mo that Miss
ltankln Is a "wonder woman," a woman
who with amazing energy has given of
herself and her money nnd her tlmo for
tho cause ot womankind, and that now
when women of Montana have the chance
to reward her, they have grasped It to
pay homngo where they feel It is due.
'Tractlcolly every nonpartisan club of
women In tho State, tho women of every
political faith, laying aside party lines have
unequivocally como out and stumped the
State for Miss ltankln." Miss Fllgclman
tells me, "for woman' of Montana say as
they cast their ballots, '"If It weren't for
Jcanctto ltankln, I couldn't be voting nt
nil ' To Jennctte ltankln more than to any
other one womnn In Montnmt Is due the
credit of winning tho right of suffrngo for
Montana women. You see bho was In
charge nf the suffrngo campaign which
swept Montana two years ago, and which
resulted In a victory at tho first referendum
over held upon tho question In our State."
In referring to the personal side of Miss,
ltankln, Miss Fligclinnn says: "Sho Is a
keen thinker, a tremendous worker, and
she has a thorough knowledge of work
In Congress, gained through her experience
an a suffrage lobblcst In two hesslons nf
Congress nnd In tho Legislatures of New
York. New Hampshire, Delawnre, Florida,
North Dakota and Montana. Sho Is prob
ably moio familiar with governmental ma
chinery than nre many of tho gentlemen
who already conBtltulo tho cog-t of the ma
chinery. She Is also entirely familiar with
social and economic conditions, having stud
led and traveled extensively throughout the
United States. Sho knows Montana's needs
too. for sho has campaigned In every
county In the Stnto. Then, too, she will
have an opportunity to work, for tho cause
of Prohibition In Congress nnd for the In
terests of the children, and she will also
work directly In Congress for the Federal
amendment.
"We women of Montana feel, too, that It
will be the most eloquent argument which
could be put to the eastern Congressmen,
who have hitherto Ignored tho demand for
national suffrage made by the enfranchised
women of the United States, to have a
woman In Congress."
    </text>
    </result>
    <result>
      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045211/1917-09-04/ed-1/seq-3/</id>
      <rel>1</rel>
      <text> 
WASHINGTON, Sept. I.
Arrests followed In qulcl ruecesslon this
afternoon when militant sufrrnglsts made
many attempts to plant suffingo banners
In front of tho Maud eretftc 1 In front of
tho White House, from which President Wil
son nnd tho Allies' diplomats were to review
tho selective service parade.
Two militants set up their banneis In
fro"ht of the stand and for fifteen minutes
were unmolested. One banner was ad
dressed to tho President and proclaimed tho
Injustlco of conscripting men while denying
their mothers a voice In the Government.
The other standard was simply tho suffrage
colors, purple, white and gold.
The first two women arrested were Miss
nieanor Calnan, of Methuen, Mass., and
Miss IMith Alngo, of Jnmestown, N. Y.
Miss Lucy Brnnnen, of Connecticut, and
Mis Adams, of Norfolk, took their places
carrying similar banners. When tho pollco
began dealing the street for the parade
they were asked to make way. They re
fused and were arrested, Mrs Annie Ar
nell, of Wilmington, Del., and Mrs. Dorothea
Bartlctt, of Putnam, Conn , carrying suf
frage colors, were arrested while attempt
ing to cros tho street, ns were Miss Mar
garet Fotherlngham of Buffalo, nnd Miss
Julia Kmery, of Baltimore.
Maud Malone, of New York, who has a
national reputation ns a Wilson heckler,
was the next to fall Into the net, with her
being arrested Mrs, William Wallace Chlla
holm, of Huntingdon, Pa,
    </text>
    </result>
    <result>
      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045211/1917-11-12/ed-1/seq-2/</id>
      <rel>1</rel>
      <text> 
WASHINGTON. Nov 12
The forty-one women arrested last Satur
day afternoon for picketing the White
House In behalf of suffrage were found
guilty In police court this afternoon. Judge
Mullowncy did not sentence thft'wpmen. but
took the case under advisement and said he
would give It "deep consideration" before
making the sentences known.
Three women from Philadelphia Mrs.
Lawrence Lewis, Miss Kllznheth McShano
and Miss Cntharlne Lincoln were nrnong
those found guilty.
Attorneys for .Mrs. Harvey Wiley, wife
of the pure food specialist, gave notice of nn
appeal nnd she ws released tinder $100
bond. The others, among wheni are Mr?.
John Winters Ilrannan. social leader or New
York, and Mrs. William Kent, wife of tin
former California Congressman, were re
leased under the $1025 collateral put up by
Miss Mary Ingham, 'if Philadelphia when
they were arrested Saturday.
The suffragists were arraigned In Court
In groups of fours, sixes nnd eights. Just
as they marched In different croups to the
White Houlie Saturday, nnd lifter each
group wbh tried and found guilty they were
asked by Judge Mullowney to step aside
until nil forty-one had been tried, when lie
said he would pronounce sentence
Hy hie careful questioning of each of the
prisoners ns to whether they had been nr
rested and sentenced heforo for n similar
orfense, It was plain that Judgo Mullowney
Intended to give "repeaters" n sentence of
perhaps six months and first-offenders only
thirty days In Jail.
Court opened promptly at nine, but It
was eleven o'clock before tlie casea of the
Suffragists wero reached on the ilocketi.
During the long wait the prisoners nnd
their friends who crowded tlie court
amused themselves exchanging newspaper
clippings nbout their arrest, knitting socks
and sweaters and discussing the recent suf
frage victory In New York.
Many of the prisoners brought suitcases,
handbags and bundles containing toilet
articles, clean underclothing arid other
articles which they Intended taking to Jail,
as all were determined not to pay fines
DOCTOR WIL.HY AIDS HIS W1FI0
Dr Harvey Wiley, of "pure food" fume,
was In court with Mrs. Wiley, who was
among the plcketers, and took a seat along
side his wife nn the front bench. With
iilm was Ravinond H. Dickey, a Washing
ton l.iwjer. who had been ictalind ns
counsel for Mrs. Wiley
Police Sergeant Lee, in charge of the de
tail which made the arrests, wan the first
witness for the Oovernment. Ho raid tho
forty-one suffragists, bearing their ban
ners, came to the White House In eight
croups at 4:30 o'clock Saturday afternoon
at a time when the Oovernment depart
ments were letting out. Hy stopping at
the west gate of the White. House they Imd
drawn n tremendous crowd, which ob
structed the sidewalks
He had told eaci. of the pickets that they
were violating the law, lie said, and dl
reeled them to move on. Only one of tho
forty-one maae any respnurw, mm iicii
they declined to move they were arrested
and taken In patrol wagons tn the station
house.
The one picket who made response, he
Bald, replied:
"I cannot move until I get directions
from our leader."
The suffragists called witnesses who said
tint crowd was not dense; and that it had
formed because the news had been spread
broadcast that the pickets would be ar
rested when thev appeared, rather than be.
cause the pickets wero there. Pickets had
stood at the White House gates for six
months and nobody paid attention to them,
tho witnesses said, until It was announced
they would be arrested, when great crowds
gathered.
Mrs John Winters Ilrannan. of New
York, who was In the first group arraigned,
made a scathing address to the Court when
Judge Mullowney asked If any of the
women wlsh-d to say anything before sen
tence was pronounced.
HOLD." PRKSIDHNT RKSPONSI1ILK
"We will hold the President responsible
for this whole thing, because he will not
urge tho passage of equal suffrage leglsln
tlou fer us," shouted Mrs. Ilrannan.
"Your courts, your policemen, your Jails,
cannot stop us in this effort to obtain equal
suffrage. Whatever the verdict or this
Cnuri may be we shall go on picketing, we
sb-ill nlcket again at once and keep it up
The responsibility for thin thing will rest
upon y mi and not uihiii us."
This aroused the Ire of Judge Mullowney.
M, handed out a vitriolic rebuke for what
be declared their wanton and willful breach
of the laws of the country .
"Do you think It is the duty of the police
to make the crowd move on and leave you
women standing there with your '";"
he asked. "I'vo tried to explain to ou In
vour various trlalB ncre inai j" - -
Tng the law und that the practice musi
Judge Mullowney If she had anything to,
say.
"I come from Utah, where I have lieen
a political worker for tlfb Democratic
party. I rare here to help In this cause,
and now I wnt to know why the Demo
cratic parly had me arrested." .
This question convulsed the courtroom In
laughter and the ballirts rapped and shouted
for order.
Judge Mullowney nlso bent nlmot double
with laughter. When he recovered hla Ju
diction composure he said:
"I'm sure I don't know, madam : you'll
have to risk somebody else."
When the group was called, which Mrs.
Wiley was a member. Lawyer Dickey said
he would represent Mrs. Wiley, but wanted
to explain carefully that he was not repre.
sentlng the other women.
He asked for n separate Jury trial for
his client, but this wis denied by the
court on tho ground that the Rlatutes do
not allow a trial hy Jury In a breach of
traffic regulation cases.
    </text>
    </result>
    <result>
      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045211/1916-11-11/ed-1/seq-6/</id>
      <rel>1</rel>
      <text> 
      
    </text>
    </result>
    <result>
      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030214/1920-08-19/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
      <rel>1</rel>
      <text> 
      Woman Vote
Expected to
Aid Harding
Republicans Believe Suf?
frage Will Help Them
in Presidential Race ;
Fear Effect on Senate
Blow Most Serious
To Wet Candidates
Democrats insist Progres?
sive Sentiment Will Al?
lure the New Voters
By Carter Field
WASHINGTON, Aug. 18.--Enfran?
chisement of women in very state is
likely to help the Republicans on the
Presidency, but, on the other hand,
help the Democrats in their fight to
control the Senate.
Political Washington was busy to?
night checking up, with a view to de?
termining how the situation would be
affected by this army of additional
voters.
By far the most prevalent view, ap?
parently, is that the women voters
will divide along pretty much the same
lines as the men in the forthcoming
election, and as a result change the
situation v^ry little. But there are a
few exceptions to thise.
Republican States Lead
Those who think Harding will get
more than the Republican share of the
women voters seem to present the
most convincing argument. They wave
aside the contention that the thirty
sixth state is Democratic, and the
women may therefore be expected to
lie grateful, by calling attention to
fact that of the thirty-six states which
did ratify the amendment twenty-nine
?-re Republicans ami only seven Demo?
cratic.
These observers say the proportion;
of women favoring prohibition is much |
greater than the proportion of drys
among the male voters. The fact that
Cox was nominated by wet political !
bosses, and that his campaign is being j
aided by a subtle moist appeal direct?
ed particularly at the wet centers of
New York, New Jersey and Wiscon?in,j
will, it is thought, result in driving aj
tremendous number of women to the
polls to vote for Harding as a rebuke
to tho wet leaders.
This view, incidentally, is strongly
held by (le?era 1 Counsel Wayne B.
Wheeler of the Anti-Saloon League.
"Not all women are dry, of course," j
Mr. WheeW tolil The Tribune corre?
spondent after hearing the news from |
Tennessee, "but" the great majority of i
women are not only dry, but anxious
to see a rigorous enforcement of the
dry laws. You will find that tho
women in this election will not vote]
for any candidate who makes an appeal j
to the hopes of the wets. Their votes
will aid tremendously the candidate
who promises strict law enforcement.
Women Foes to Liquor Interests
"Then, too, the women know that the j
liquor forces have always opposed I
woman suffrage because of the knowl- j
edge of the wets that women would ;
vote for prohibition. So they have
come to regard the liquor interests as
their enemies, with the result that
their desire to end the liquor traffic is
given an added incentive."
Democrats here wave this aside, say?
ing that prohibition is not an issue
in this campaign and that the women
voters, being naturally more eager!
about progressive legislation, will
naturally turn to the more progressive
candidates, not only for President, but |
for Senators and members of the House |
of Representatives. They say the
granting of the ballot to the women
of all 111?' states will be of enormous
h elf) to Cox and to the winning of a
Democratic Senate and House.
The state in which the wet and dry
element is ant to enter stronger than
any other, it is said, is New Jersey, j
The tremendous vote given Governor i
Edwards, running on a "Wet as the!
Atlantic Ocean" platform last year, |
has encouraged the Democrats to be- |
lieve that they could overcome the,
normally tremendous Republican ma-!
jority in that stale and win its four.
27,000,000
Women Have
Right to Vote
Tennessee's Ratification
Gives 9,500,000 More
Right to Vote for Next
President in the Fall
Fight Begun in 1848
Campaign Opened in Seneca
Falls Started Movement
Which Enveloped World
Woman suffrage was won for the
women of all the states in the Union
when Tennessee, th'e thirty-sixth state,
ratified the Federal amendment. Ap?
proximately 27,000,000 women will be
entitled to vote in the Presidential
election this fall. State suffrage al?
ready ha^l enfranchised 17.500,000, and
ratification adds to this number 9,500,
000.
Thii marks the end of the women's
campaign for the ballot which began
obscurely in a little meeting in Seneca
Falls, N. Y., in 1848, swept across this
country, and extendea the political
freedom of women to nearly every
other nation in the civilized world.
Fifteen states in the United States
already had conferred full franchise
rights on women, and in fifteen others
women were entitled to vote for Presi?
dent and for certain municipal offices,
but not for members of Congress.
The suffrage amendment resolution
was passed by the Congress on June 4,
19li). Its wording was that of the orig?
inal Susan B. Anthony amendments,
drawn up by the pioneer suffragist soon
after the Civil War had enfranchised
the colored people and following the
form of the Fifteenth Amendment. It
reads:
"The right of citizens of the United
States to vote shall not be denied or
abridged by the United States or by
any state' on account of sex.
"Congress shall have power by ap?
propriate legislation to enforce the
provisions of this article."
Dates of Ratification
Thirty-six states ratified the woman
suffrage amendment in the following
order:
R?In Regular Session (10)
S?In Special Session (20)
In 1919
1. Illinois .R June 10
2. Wisconsin .R June 10
3. ?Michigan .S June 10
4. Kansas ..R June 16
5. Ohio .~R June 16
6. New York. . . .-..S June 16
7. Pennsylvania.R June 24
8. Massachusetts .R June 25
9. Texas .R June 28
10. Iowa .S July 2
11. Missouri .S July 3
12. Arkansas .S July 28
13. Montana .S July 30
M.Nebraska .S Aug. 2
15. Minnesota .S Sept. 8
16. New Hampshire.S Sept. 10
17. Utah .'..S Sept. 30
18. California.S Nov. 1
10. Maine .S Nov. 5
20. North Dakota.S Dec. 1
21. South Dakota.S Dec. 4
22. Colorado.S Dec. 12
In 1920
23. Rhode Island.R Jan. 6
24. Kentucky .R Jan. 6
25. Oregon .S Jan. 12
26. Indiana .S Jan. 16
27. Wvoming .S Jan. 27
28. Nevada .S Feb. 7 ?
29. New Jersey.R Feb. 0 !
30. Idaho .S Feb. 11 ;
31. Arizona .S Feb. 12
32. New Mexico.S Feb. 10
33. Oklahoma .S Feb. 28
34. West Virginia.S Mch. 10
35. Washington .S Mch. 22
36. Tennessee .S Aug. 18
Failed to Ratify
1. Alabama. 5 South Carolina.
2. Georgia. 6. Virginia.
3. Maryland. 7. Delaware.
4. Mississippi. 8. Louisiana.
Special Sessions Called
The fact that many state legislatures ;
did not hold regular sessions in 1920,
and would be required to call special
sessions if the .suffrage amendment
were to become effective in time f?ir
the Presidential elections, was the last
great obstacle the suffrage movement
had to overcome. Even in states ?
where the women had voted for I
many years and where ratification was
more or less an accepted fact the Gov?
ernors hesitated to call special ses- !
sions, for reasons of economy, or be?
cause of local political issues which
threatened to become embarrassing.
Governor Allen of Kansas came, to the
Colby Agrees
To Speed Final
?Suffrage Step
Secretary of State Will
Proclaim Ratification as!
Soon as Tennessee Sends
the Official Notice;
Pioneers To Be Honored
Anthony, Slanton and Molt
Busts To Be Placed in
Capitol at Washington !
WASHINGTON, Aug. 18. Prompt;
promulgation of the Federal woman ?
suffrage amendment, should the action
of the Tennessee Legislature to-day be
confirmed, was promised by Secretary
Colby when word of the vote at Nash?
ville reached the State Department. He
was prepared, Mr. Colby said, to issue
the necessary proclamation immediate?
ly on receipt of official notice that
Tennessee had ratified the amendment.
j When the word of ratification came
| officials of the National Woman's party !
at once sought assurances from Secre?
tary Colby that the official action pro- j
mulgating the amendment would not I
be delayed. They also urged their rep?
resentatives in Nashville to see that no
time was lost in forwarding the official
notice to the State Department.
The woman's party also announced
that steps toward a national celebra-1
tion at the cankar liad been taken. The'
date will be fixed later, and included in !
the ceremonies will be the presentation
to the national Capitol of marble busts'
of the rtio of suffrage pioneers Susan j
B. Anthony, Elizabeth Cady Stanton
and Lucretia Mott -which it is hop'-d i
will be placed either in the Hall of
Fame or the rotunda of the great !
building. The statue of Frances Wil
lard, presented by Illinois, is the only;
woman's figure now in the Hall of
Fame.
There still is suffrage work to be
? done, the National American Woman ;
I Suffrage Association emphasized in a |
I statement issued from the headquar- I
i ters here yesterday. The association
j takes it for granted that opposition to
the Susan B. Anthonv amendment will i
continue to develop and will show itself
in court action to prevent the amend- i
ment becoming operative.
The association declares it is pre-j
paring to meet any attacks which may
be made in this direction. "It expects
the Secretary of State to proclaim the
amendment at once as ratified," the'
statement says. "This would seem to
be automatically inevitable. Even if
the amendment is to be the subject of
later attack, the Secretary of State's ;
immediate task is the proclamation.1
Without the proclamation there is no ?
amendment to attack."
The word "male" will not have to bei
stricken from state constitutions, be?
cause it is "read out by the amendment ?
itself," the statement asserts. The
opinion of Charles E. Hughes is quoted
in support, of this contention.
"Can the Presidential election be
thrown out if women participate in it?"
the statement asks. Its answer is:
"Opponents could no more throw out
the Presidential election or find any;
grounds upon which to raise such a ;
hope than they could cause the sun, to |
stsnd still." But the suffragists, the ,
statement says, wi?'?M have ground to!
throw out an election if women were
denied the rigrit to participate.
"Suffragists long ago ceas?jd to je
frightened at anti-suffrage threats,"
the statement say-, "none of which was
ever quite so fatuous as this one."
Victory Won
By 49 to 47
After Hope
Had Faded
Unexpected Votes of Two
Men Swung to Resolu?
tion at Critical Stage
Saved Cause of Women
Amendment Fought
By Powerful Lobby
Leaders Confident Effort
to Reconsider Will Be
Futile; Colby Is Ready
to Issue Proclamation
, Special Dispatch *o The Tribu-"
NASHVILLE, Tenn., Aug:. 18.?i
The Tennessee House of'Representa?
tives to-day ratified the Susan ?.
Anthony amendment to the Federal
Constitution giving the suffrage to
women. Unless a motion to recon?
sider, which comes up to-morrow at
10:30 o'clock, is successful ratifi?
cation will have been completed by
the thirty-six ?tales necessary to
make it effective.
The vote by which the resolution
was adopted was 4!) to 47. Speaker
Seth Walker, opponent of suffrage,
changed his vete in order to move
for reconsideration, so that the if?
ricial vote stands 50 to 46.
The Tennessee Senate ratified ?a-?;
Friday by a vote of 25 to 4. If the
House to-morrow votes down the mo?
tion to reconsider all that will re?
main to give women the suffrage
throughout the country will lie a
proclamation by Secretary of State
Colby at Washington. Secretary
Colby will issue this proclamation as
soon as the action of the Tennessee
Legislature is formally certified to
him.
By the amendment 9,500,000 wom?
en will be added to the 17,r>00,000
who, by state enactment, already
possess the suffrage.
Mow Parties Lined L'p
The l?ne-up of the parties in to
vote was:
Democrats Aye, 35; nay, 34; ab?
sent. 1.
Republicans Aye, 1">; nay, 12; ab?
sei:?., 2.
The line-up in the Senate last Fri?
day was:
Democrats Aye, 18; nay, ?*.
Republicans Aye, 7; nay, 1.
In preparation for the final vote to
morrow both s;?:?-s are busy Lo night,
the suffragists stiffening their li
that a vote may r.?.?t be lost and the
antis doing then- utmost to win ovei
enough members to turn defeat into vie
ory.
The antis had a two hour confe?enc?
behind closed doors in a hotel i ion
here to-night. The decision was t?
inspire telegrams from every countj
??f the state to members reproaching
them for thei r v? te for rat il
ITiey intend t?i get a hundred <?r s?
messages to each suffrage member, an?
many more t?> the two who made vie
tory jui isible.
SufFrage leaders arc taking steps t?
counteract tins, having suffrage friend
express through the" wires their ap
preciation for the votes of the'.
friends. They believe the antis wil
gain nothing by their maneuver.
A bill has already been drawn b
Jud&e Joseph Higgins, president o
the Tennessee Constitutional Leagm
tu stop Secretary of State Colby froi
promulgating Tennessee's action. ]
will be served when the Legislature
action becomes binding by defeat c
?apse of the House motion to recoi
sider.
Wh?-n the House session bpga
morning there were few present v.!
did not believe that suffrage wi
doomed to ie:' at. The cards v. ire a
-;. - . ?I against ratification. A '.
day and Tuesday new
workers had been pouring into ' ih]
ville. Claim agents, legislative atto
neys, "fixers," lawyers allied with 0
anti-lobby came in on each trai
Secret wires were pulled ami seci
pressure applied. How powerful the
influences wen- is seen in the fact t:.
of the sixty-two pledged t-> vote f
ratification only forty-nine did so. li
the lobby could not get enough.
found itself unabU- to sway tv.?> mc
who had all along been consider
doubtful, ami these two men, L-y t
unshaken way they clung to th?
pledges, enabled the House? to ratify.
Doubtful Vote Clinches Victory
One Democrat and one Republic
aru this afternoon comfortably e
sconced in the suffrage hall of fan
Representative Harry T. Barns, Repi
I-can, had long been classed doubtf
He had been given up again and again
suffragists. On motion to table t
resolution, he vot'd to table. B
when the roll call on ratification can
bis ''aye" ran?? out throughout the hi
and gav'e to suffrage the chance to ti
The other man was Hanks Turner
Denn?-rat. Hy too had been given i
No one counted on him. But on the n
tions to table he voted with th.. s
fragists. When the final roll call cat
Burns'? vote gave an a?lv ntage of o
The motion to table had twice been 48
48 and with Burns's exception :
remained the same down to Turn<
name. Speaker Seth Walker was ?
ting by Turner, talking to him
earnest and emphatic tdfiea.
Turner pas<u>d. What was up?
    </text>
    </result>
    <result>
      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn89066315/1920-08-26/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
      <rel>1</rel>
      <text> 
      WOMEN'S RIGHT TO
VOTE NOW PART OF
THE CONSJITUTIQN
Proclamation Signed by Sec
"fyof State ColbvEarh
I his Morning At Home':
Prepared Last Night.
LEADERS CHEER
WHEN TOLD NEWS
Are Disappointed When IN
formed There Would Not
Be Public Ceremony: No
Leader Selected.-
By Halted Press"
WASHINGTON'. Aug. ?6.The right
of women to vote became a part of
the Constitution of the United States
here today when Secretary ot State.
Colby proclaimed the Nineteenth
Amendment a part ot the Constitution.
The proclamation was signed early
this morning at the home ot the Sec
retary. It had been prepared last
night .
Suffrage leaders were summoned to
the State Department as soon . tk.
proclamation was signed and notified
of the action. They cheered wildly
when they were told that the amend.
ment had been made operative. They
naa been expecting a public ceremony
however, and seemed to be quite dis
appointed when they learned that
there would be none. Theyasked
for a repeating of the ceremony in or
der that moving pictures could be tak. .
en and that suffrage leaders could take
part in the ceremony. Colby replied
that he would consider the matter and
reUred to his private office. The suf
frage leaders then held a Jubilee at
heir headquarters. Miss Alice Paul
announced that they would not relax
their vigilance In the least to see that
the women of the country did not lose
the right which they have recently
won.
Colby later announced that the rea
son why there was no public cere
mony was because he was not sure
which group of leaders should take
part In the ceremony. He announced
that different groups ot women had
argued, the question .last .night foc-a,,.
Ions time-without coming to any cop-,
elusion whatever.
    </text>
    </result>
  </results>
</topic>
</topics>

<topics>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-heroin-crisis/selected-articles</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84022472/1912-12-13/ed-1/seq-5/</id>
	      <rel>1</rel>
	      <text>
STATE BOARD WILL
STRIVE TO STAMP
OUT DRUG ABUSES
Victims of the "Bing" Habit
Here May be Counted by
the Hundreds'
Pharmacy Commissioners Will
Revoke on Specific Complaint
Claiming Discretionary Power
i
PtesMent John A. Leverty of the
estate Board of Pharmaoy OommiMlon
ra stated to a. Fumar reporter today
that th board stands ready to aot
agalxust th sal of opium, heroin and
other narvating drags In cases where
specific ahargu are brought. The
board takes Jurisdiction upon th
ground that it has discretionary pow-
-violated.
There is no law In this State against
the sale of morphine or its derivatives
iu.t the board is of the opinion that
th pharmacy laws are not intended
to provide a meani for victims of
drag habits to purchase drugs with
.Immunity.
Concerning the recent case in this
-c3tjF -where the board took aotlon Pres
ident leverty stated: "We would not
have been able to take action If spe
cific charges had not been made.
There ie no doubt there are a large
number of heroin users in Connec
ticut, but the sellers of the stuff (If
4T-tifrfiital cannot be Dunished bevond
the revocation of their pharmacy li
censes ; until the legislature enacts a
itatute similar to the oocaina law.
The crusade being conducted in
JJfew York against heroin has made
this state a haven for the users of the
drug. New Haven has passed an or
dmanoe against the sale of the stuff
nd the result is that the users - are
coming to Bridgeport to purchase.
"Already there is a substitute for
heroin on the market. It is called
dlonln' ethyl morphine hydrochlorate)
ana the law that does not cover all
?i-u mm of a morphine derivative will
Have little effeot in stamping out the
""n" understand that the Bridgeport
aldermen are to pass an ordinance at
Its next meeting. If they specify
heroin alone and do not specify all
drugs of a morphine derivative they
will leave loopholes for the users to
crawl through."
"Bing" Is the slang name of the
drug used bv the drug slaves here. It
Is estimated that there are between
pno and 400 users of the drug in this
oity Its line is said to have been
first introduced here by habitueB of
mo nnderworid. -who taught the possi
bilities of producing soothing sensa
tions to young men and boys they
mt in lunch rooms and pool and bil
liard halls. The drug users are now
-i n h found among factory work
ers and clerks who carry the stuff
in the sawea on iuu aa. luuuiam
Heroin is said to produce a, feeling
that makes the user feel as though
he owned the world and its users loose
their aopetlte for food while their
craving for tobacco in cigarette form
increases. Increased doses are needed
from time to time to satisfy the de
sires. The stuff is expensive and one
young man who is employed In a
n'rf End factory recently went to
;Nw Tork and bought $18 worth of
the stuff, spending nis enure pay mr
a. week in order to have a supply on
hand.
Rarelv a month passes without at
least one death in this city directly
traceable to the ravages of the drug
habit.
        </text>
    </result>
    <result>
	      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn87055779/1913-12-08/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	      <rel>1</rel>
	      <text>
        SAY THAT DH. FINK
PRESCRIBED
South Rend Physician KGo Be
fore State Medical Board To
morrow in a Case for Re
vocation of License.
Special io News-Times:
INDIANAPOLIS, Dec. S. The state
board of medicad registration and ex
amination will meet here Tuesday to
hear evidence against Dr. II. A. Fink,
a prominent South Bend physician,
charged with prescribing heroin for
minors. The action is for a revocation
of Dr. Fink's license.
The charge was liled by attorneys
for 2"sewton Ilolycross, a South Bend
contractor, who charges the prescrip
tion was given his son, Raymond, by
Dr. Fink. The boy is said to have
purchased the dru -at Paul Wolter's
drug store in South Bend on the pre
scription. The charge is iilcd under the act
passed by the legislature at the last
session in which heroin was put on
the "black list" and physicians forbid
den to prescribe the drug to u-i ir.
A short time ago, it is charged,
yonng Ilolycross' parents noticed he
was acting peculiarly, as if under the
influence of a drug. After close ques
tioning the boy is said to have broken
down and admitted the purchase of
tho drug through the prescription,
naming- the physician. The charges
were prepared immediately and filed
with the state beard.
Raymond Ilolycross was one of the
boys involved in the -drug" expose
in South Bend last winter when sev
eral South Bend druggists were ar
rested charged with furnishing the
"dope" to minors. The cases were
dismissed, however, when it was found
the statute did not cover the particu
lar drug, heroin, which the boys had
been taking. They were lirst sup
plied the drug through an Assyrian,
Solomon Neimer. it was claimed, who
acted as a purchasing agent.
The agitation resulting from this
expose was the cause of the introduc
tion of the bill to prohibit the sale
or prescription of heroin to persons
known to be users.
The act provides that a physician
shall lose his license if convicted of
prescribing the drug to an habitual
user. In criminal proceedings a line
of $ur or not more than 5G00 and im
prisonment in the county jail not le
than io days or inr- than a year, is
provided for the lirst offense. For the
second offense the line is not less than
$-j00 or more than 51.00 and im
prisonment in the penitentiary from
one to eight years.
Druggists who sell heroin on pre
scription must keep a record of such
sales and report to the state board of
pharmacy.
        </text>
    </result>
        <result>
	      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045211/1914-09-14/ed-1/seq-3/</id>
	      <rel>1</rel>
	      <text>
        Tells Amazing Story of the
Ease With Which He
Was Able to Buy Nerve
Qestroying Substances.
Twenty-four houra out of a potlco cell,
a toy of 1. Pale, thin anl hardly able to
, uK one foot after the other, told today
),ow he took to uslni? cocaine and heroin
nd what the drug have done to him In
the Iwo yeara.he has been their victim.
William Schaffer, 822 Olive street, Is the
hoy He was arrested as a. disorderly
character. Magistrate Tracy, at the
Eleventh and Winter streets station, gave
him his freedom yesterany. ouuy .., -Klns
his light against tho drugs.
chaffer Is a flaxen-hnlred youth who
n fairly sturdy In the dayB before ho
began experimenting with heroin. Ho
weighed about HO pounds then. Today
ills weight Is down to 120 and tho clothes
he wears are sizes too large, though once
they ntted him. His head hangs weakly
and he has trouble walking moro than a
few steps.
Schaffer has been treated twice for tho
drug habit. Onco It was In tho House of
ri i pctlon. where he sreved three month
nfter stealing from a department store to
get money for the drugs. A month ngo
he was discharged as cured from the
mlladelphla Hospital.
"But ou can't keep away from It
.around here," Schaffer explained, as he
told his stoo. "I kept away from the i
drugs two weeks nnd then two men Held
gome heroin before me. I've been pretty
bad since then."
His being "pietty bad" resulted In an
attack of heart failure, which caused his
arrest. When Patrolman MoKonna, of
the Eleventh nnd Winter streets Btatlon,
found that Schafter was not drunk, tho
boy was sent to tho Hahnemann Hos
pital and then back to tho police station.
"J had a close call," said Schaffer. "I
was filled with heroin and cocalno all day
and a convulsion got me. That's the way
they all die," he added, shaking his head.
Scharter can clear up me mHiery inai
surrounds the making of 17-ye.ir-old co
caine fiends.
"Hard to get cocaine? Well, I should
say not'' he exclaimed. "I never had
any trouble buying all I wanted when I
had the money. Did they mind selling to
a boy? They did not. I could show you
a good many drug stores where you can
buy It now. But most of It comes from
the cocaine peddlers.
"J started taking drugs Just about two
y fiats ago I used to stay around a pool
room at Eighth and Vine streets. Tho
fellows In there asked mo If I didn't want
to try some heroin. So I did. I took it
every day for a month and then I thought
I'd stop. But I couldn't"
Tho only limes since then that the
Schaffer boy has lived without drugs have
been the periods Just following his re
lease from hospitals.
"1 worked for some chemists at Eighth
aiid Callowhlll streets when I first began
lifllng the stuff," Schaffer went on. "But
7 couldn't hold on long after the habit
fcot Yne. I started taking one tablet of
one-sixth of a grain a day, Saturday I
took 35 tablets.
"Of course, I didn't always have money
to buy heroin. I used to steal things from
department stores when I needed money.
Once you get tho habit you can't go more
than three or four hours without heroin.
"I used to take little things from the
counters and I never got caught. But
Inst march I picked up somo Jewelry and
they caught mo out on tho lHvnik."
Schaffer was sentenced to three months I
In the Houso of Correction for that. p
" rtieasea on June 6 and then got work
A SELF-CONFESSED BOY DRUG VICTIM
William Schaffer, who tried heroin "to see what it was like," tells how boys
are made drug fiends and his own experiences trying to break the habit.
man. Ho held some heroin undor my
nose and then 1 Just had to buy It. They
sell two tablets for a nickel. Since then
I have been taking 25 or .10 tablets a
day."
Schaffer says he has taken heroin for
tho last. "I'm scared," he declared. "I
know what happens nnd thoy all die when
they get like I am. I'm going to stop,"
Schaffer thinks getting out of tho city
to a farm Is the best way to keen from
Using more drugs.
"But what chance havp I got'?" he
akcd. "I don't know where I enn go.
Sure, I know lots of other young fellows
who are taking drugs. How old are they?
Oh, 16 nnd 17 and some younger, Any
one can huy the stuff If thoy know where
to go."
        </text>
    </result>
        <result>
	      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045389/1915-02-17/ed-1/seq-9/</id>
	      <rel>1</rel>
	      <text>
        HARRISON DRUG ACT !
TIRES EFFECT MARCH I
JKvery Physician nnd DruKKlnt Must
Register With Revenue
Collector.
Requires Actual Inventory of Cocaine
and Morphine, With Record of All |
Sales and Purchases, Open to CJov- 1
eminent Inspectors.
In compliance with the Harrison drug
act, approved on Dec'cmbcr 17, 1914,
prescribing tho manner In which cer
tain hablt-formlng drugs shall be
manufactured or dispensed, the United
mates Internal Revenue ofTlco Is ready
to Issue the special stamps and order
Ijlanks which the law provides. Every
physician, druggist, dentist and veter
inary surgeon handling any of the
drugs coming under the Harrison act
is required to register with the Col
lector of Internal Revenue previous to
March 1. A heavy penalty is prescribed
for nil those coming under tho pro
visions of tho ajt who fall to have
special stamps bv March 1, If they
have in their possession any opium or
roru leaven, their salts or derivatiesT
or any preparation manufactured from
tliem. Collector Moncure has made ar
rangements with the various division
deputy' collectors to have placed In
the hands of all those who come under
the act the necessary application blank,
known as form 678. Upon receipt by
the collector of the application the
registry number -will be Klven, and
every physician. drugKist, dentist and
veterinary surgeon will he required to
make tho order under his registered
number.
PHARMACY HOARD SKS IIS
Ot:'!' COPIHS OK ACT
The Internal revenue regulations de
scribing the requirements of the Har
rison act havo been published by the
Commissioner of Internal Revenue for
the guidance of those concerned, and In
addition the Stato Board of Pharmacy
has published a pamphlet for the In
formation of all pharmacists In Vir
ulnla.
It is tho purpose of Collector Mon
cure, who ;as given Bitch instructions
to all division deputy collectors, to
co-operate with State ofll'-erx looking
to the enforcement of the law.
Up to tho close of business yester
day afternoon, the collector's office had
received 1J0 applications for registry.
It Is understood that there are about
21.000 pharmacists In Virginia. 50 per
cent of whom will have to register
with Collector Hart, who has Jurisdic
tion over the western part of tho
State.
Collector Moncure has appointed
Franklin Harwood a deputy collector
under tho Harrison a<t, the appoint
ment having become effective on Feb
ruary io. Chief Deputy Thomas 1\
Mtanv in in charge of the collection
in this district.
Ml'ST ItBOlSTKIl I t I.I.
.VAMK A.M? AlinttKSK
It Is required by the act that every
person who produce.", imports, manu
factures, _corn pounds, deals In, dispenses,
'?Up. distributes or gives away opium
? ?r coca leaves or any compound of
liber, shall register It's name or style,
place or places of business, and, if lie
ban no office, then bis residence. No
physician, dentist or veterinarian may
have In bis possession or write a pre
scription for any opium or cocaine
preparation unless he has first reg
istered with the collector of Internal
ievenue of bin district and has paid
the tax of n. Aft'-r compliance with
tlils formula he will bo required to
use on every prescription for the drugs
named. In order to b.iy any of them,
the serial number Klven him. lie musrt
make out a duplicate of every order
or prescription, and keep the duplicates
on file for at leant two years
The prescription must be written,
signed by the prescriber's name in
full and be dated as of the. day 11
? signed, and must show the pre
server's serial number and the loca
tion of bis office and the name and
address of the patient for whom It
Is Issued. The prescriptions must not
be refilled.
ACCI HATE I.WK.N TOIJ V
is m:<u iiti:ti u\ i.wv
Kvery person, firm or com,>aty dis
pensing directly to consumers any of
the drugs referred to must keep an
accurate inventory of all such atock
as ho has on band, anJ must verify
the Inventory by oath not later than
March 5.
According to the pamph'.e; issued by
the' State Board of Pharmacy the act
absolutely prohibits Tho sulo of lauda
num, Squlbb's Mixture, Sun Cholera
<"'ure, Dovers's I'owder, codeine and
preparations containing more than two
grains of opium, one-fourth grain of
morphine, one-eighth grain of heroin
or ono Kralti of C0'lei'>e to the ounce,
except upon the prescription of a
doctor registered under the act, or upon
the revenue order blanks; and these
preparations may no longer be sold by
merchants and retail dealers. Posses
sion of any of th?so drugs, oxcept in
compliance with the act, will lie con
sidered presumptive evidence of a vio
lation of the act.
The penalty for violation of any of
the requirements of the acts is a fine
of not more than f^'.OOO or Imprison
ment for not more than five years, or
b?th, in the discretion of the court.
        </text>
    </result>
    <result>
	      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045389/1916-05-28/ed-1/seq-48/</id>
	      <rel>1</rel>
	      <text>
a New Principle of
Judge Howard, Who Has Made a New Interpretation of
Law, Which Holds a Druggist Accountable lor
Damages to Parents Where He Injures the
Earning Ability of a Son by Supplying
Him with a Habit-Forming Drug
Opinion of the five Judges of the Appellate Division, writ
ten by Justice Wesley O. Howard, affirming the verdict
of the Court awarding $j,ooo to the mother for the dam
age done in destroying a son's services, to which she was
legally entitled.
A MOTHER brings this action against a drug firm for having
sold to hor -minor son a certain poisonous drug known as
?heroin. She alleges that as a jesult of these sales her
son became an habitual U6er of heroin and thereby became a
physical and moral wreck, unable to perform any labor and that
his health -was ruined and his mind destroyed, whereby she was
deprived of his services and. has been greatly damaged. The
facts were submitted'to a jury and a Verdict returned in favor
?f the plaintiff for $2,000 compensatory damages and $1,000
punitive damages.
Our examination of tne records convinces us that the num
erous sales of this drug to this boy continuing over a long
period of time have been established by overwhelming evidence.
And we believe that the evidence shows that the plaintiff was,
in fact, actually damaged. The proof showB that" previous to his
acquisition of the drug habit the young man earned considerable
money.
The action is said to be a novel one. Tn 'some respects this
is true. By whatever name this action may go the fact is that
the property rights of tho plaintiff have been trespassed upon
and she is simply suing for reimbursement The services of
her sob. to which she was legally entitled, have been destroyed,
so she alleges and so the Jury found, and she is only asking pay
for this damage done.
The plaintiff bases her claim upon the same principle which
underlies the cause of action accruing to a father in ca30 of the
abduction of his daughter, or to a husband in case of the aliena*
tlon of his wife's affections. Precedent ib not necessary In order
that the plaintiff may recover here. If tho rights of the plaintiff
have been Invaded, there must be redresB.
On one occasion 1,000 pills were Bold to him In a week?
enough poison to kill many normal people. But notwithstanding
thi3 condition of affairs, amply proven at the trial, the defendants
complain of the punitive damages which have been assessed
againBt them. Unless there is either evil intent on the part of
the defendant, or a reckless disregard of the right6 of others,
there can be no punitive damages. The evidence In this case
does not go to the extent of establishing an evil purpose to de
stroy the health and activities of this young man; 'but the proof
does abundantly establish, In our Judgment, that the defendants
were wholly reckless of the rights of others.
It establishes that the defendants. Impelled by the ln3tlnct
for gain and profit, absolutely disregarding the health and future
of this young man, and wholly unmindful of the consequences to
his parents, sold him this drug and continued to sell it to him
long after they discovered Its deleterious effects upon his system.
To say that they did this innocently affronts the reason. These
defendants were pharmacists, skilled in the science of mixing
drugs; they knew their purposes, usee and effects. They knew
the subtle, sinister destructive effect on the human syBtem of
Ihis offspring of opium. They knew of its malicious and uncon
querable mastery over the human mind?knew of its inexorable
demands upon Its victlmB.
But it was not necessary to be a pharmacist to know this;
every layman knows it. However, in the face of this general
knowledge of the baneful effects of
heroin, and in the face of their con
stant dally observation of the actual
deadly effects upon the victim whom
they were supplying with it, these de
iendants, actuated only by greed, con
tlnued for many months to sell it to thlB young m:
deluded companions.
During the time which these defendants were sup
drug to a young man he "became a vagabond, an id!
fiend and a criminal; undutiful to his mother, wortfnl
self and dangerous to the community. The Jury w
concluding that all this was the result of the Illicit tri
on by these defendants and that they should be pi
their reckless disregard of the rights amT welfare <
and his mother.
Story of the Ruin of the
Widow's Son
IN awarding a mother, a widow, 53,000 damages against
a druggist who sold to lier son, a minor, quantities
of heroin during a period of several years, a Su
preme Court jury sitting in Schenectady, New York, has
established a precedent making it just as criminal to
destroy the efficiency of a boy as it would be to injure
a man's property, his horse' or cow.
Hitherto persons who sold to young men drugs or
alcoholic drinks which damaged their health could bo
prosecuted only on the legal technicalities prohibiting
the sale of drugs without a prescription or the sale
of drugs to minors.
What Is of nation wide interest and significance in
'the verdict accorded the mother of I?eo Rooney, of
Schenectady, New York, is that it makes the scoun
drels who for petty and sordid profit hand out to
young men poisons that ruin them in body and mind
legally responsible for the destruction of their moral
? ^character and practical efficiency. The verdict of
the Supreme Court jury, the first of its kind ever ren
dered, was recently carried before the Appelate Divi
sion in the fight made by the druggists accused of
celling "dope" was unanimously upheld.
In the opinion written by Justice Wesley O. Howard,
of Troy, In which four other judges concurred, it is
stated that the evidence produced in this particular
case proved that the mother of young Rooney had
been actually damaged. Inasmuch as previous to the
boy's demoralization through the drug habit he had
earned considerable money, and that in the deprivation
of services to which she was legally entitled the prop
erty rights of the mother had been trespassed upon.
"The plaintiff bases her claim upon the same prin
ciple which underlies the cause of action accruing to
a father In case of the abduction of his daughter, or
to a husband In case of the alienation of his wife's
affection," declared the-judges. "Precedent is not nec
essary in order that the plaintiff may recover here.
If the rights of the plalntift have been Invaded; there
must be redress."
According to this decision any parent whose son is
sold drugs or alcohol to such a degree that his char
acter and efficiency are destroyed may take action
against the olfendcr for the actual damage done.
^ Judge Howard and his confrere's decision makes it
as criminal to undermine a boy's health by selling
him drugs as it is to administer poison to a neighbor's
horse.
Four years ago Loo Rooney. of Schenectady, N. Y.,
was ar, alert, bright, rosy-cheeked, normal boy. lie
was industrious, obedient, and of help to his widowed
mother. He was employed by the General Electric
Company,.of Schenectady, at a salaiy of $50 a month,
and was regarded by his superiors as one'of the most
promising young men in their employ. In addition
to his salary he often earned from SIO to ?15 a week
singing at entertainments and in theatres.
The change that took place i;i this youth within two
years was as startling and sinister as the transforma
tion of a Dr. Jt-kyll into a .Mr. Hyde. From a healthy,
rosy-cheeked boy of eighteen, young Rooney became
a physical wreck. From a happy-dispositioned boy, al
ways eager to help his mother and to be of service
to hit, employers, he dovdoped into a vagabond, a
retusing to work, stealing whatever he could
in ordet r; secure the drug. He became physically de
formed. his character became insolent, ugly,, morose
and sullen.' Hie health ruined to the degree that he
was unable to perform any labor, his mind destroyed,
this boy, in whom a mother once took tender pride,
has goue alotg a road to ruin leading through the
Schenectady County Jail, the Albany Penitentiary,
the Fonda Jail to the Elmlra Reformatory, where ha
Js at present confined.
f Week by week, while the degenerative process was
going on, the druggist accused?C. B. Skinner, of
C. fe. Skinner & Company, Amsterdam, N. Y.?handed
out, according to the testimony produced in Court,
this baleful and deadly poison. Week by week, for
an insignificant sum of money, for what muBt have
netted only a meagre, and sorry profit, this boy was
sold from three hundred to six hundred heroin pills.
One week, according to the testimony, one thousand
pills were sold to him?enough to kill, declared Dr.
B. R. Kirscliberg, city chemist, of Schenectady, one
hundred normal persons.
Before his eyes, week by week and month by month,
this druggist could not fail to see the ghastly effects
of the poison he -was purveying?the fading of color
in the boy's cheeks, tho growing sallowne-ss of the
complexion, the rings deepening under his dull, sullen
eyes, the palsied tremor of his arms as he reached for
the drug. He could not have failed to see the villainy
working?no more than the poisoner who deliberately
watches his victim, no less than the saloonkeeper who
sells whiskey to young men day by day over a bar.
How the Drug Sapped His Health
and Made His Mind Diseased
According to Justice Howard, the proof furnished
abundantly established that the druggists, "impelled
by the instinct for gain and profit, absolutely disre
garding tlie health and future of this young man, and
wholly unmindful of tho consequences to his parents,
sold him this drug and continued to sell ii to him
long after they discovered its deleterious effects upon
his system." For the pills sold the druggist received
seventy-five cents a hundred. ? On the single sale of
one thousand pills?enough to kill one hundred per
sons?they received $7.50.
Shortly after the theft of a large quantity of raw
heroin by young Rooney from another drugstore in
Amsterdam, the boy's cousin, James Murry, was found
dying in the. .Rooney house from drug poisoning. It
is believed by local authorities that his death was
due to an overdose of heroin. In the legal proceedings
it was brought out that the heroin habit had been
contracted by a number of other young men ia
Schenectady. Young Hooney's mother, at present em
ployed as a clerk in a department store in Schenec
tady, admitted in court that she had expended her
entire savings of $2,000 in endeavoring to reform
her son.
The story of young Roonoy's downfall can possibly
be duplicated in many other communities where young
men are sold drugs by unscrupulous druggists. Leo
liooney at the age of eighteen possessed much of the
natural curiosity of youth. When, about four years
ago, William Slavin, a pal, told him wonderfully pleas
ant dreams could be obtained by taking a certain
drug, Rooney was anxious to try it. He Avas given
several pills and?being totally Ignorant of the hide
ously destructive effects of this product of opium?
said he would ,like to get more.
According to the * testimony furnished in court,
Rooney was taken by his friend to tho drugstore of
C. B. Skinner & Co., No. 8 East Main street, Amster
dam, which Is fifteen miles from Schenectady, and was
Introduced to C. B. Skinner as being "all right."
On January 1, 1912, ho made his first purchase of
heroin tablets, securing two hundred tablets, for
which he paid $1.50. These tablets were sold to him
without his presenting a physician's prescription, nor
was his name entered on the "poison book" in the
store. After his first purchase the boy, according to
his declaration, bought plllB regularly almost every
week up until June 5. 1914, a period of nearly two and
a half years.
Month by month the fatal power of the drug took
hold of him and he became a confirmed user of the
dope. He sometimes took from six to eight pills an
hour. His purchases averaged from three hundred to
six hundred pills a week. Sometimes hiB dally con
sumption was ae high as seventy-flve to one hundred
tablets. One week he made the astounding purchase
of oue thousand tablets. These tablets were all one
twelfth or one-eighth of a grain each. During the
proceedings brought by the boy's mother against the
druggist it was testified that on no occasion did Skin
ner placo the pills in a bottle bearing a poison label
as Is required by law.
C. B. Skinner, the druggist accused, has been a
pharmacist since 1892. He graduated from the
University of Buffalo in 1S98. The other member of
the firm, S. W. Skinner, is in charge of a drug store
in Illon, N. Y. This concern, accuhed of selling to a
young boy one thousand heroin tablets in a single
week for the sum of $7.50, is reported to be worth
$40,000.
In November, 1912, the boy declared that Druggist
Skinner asked him if his mother knew that he was
using heroin. "Not to my knowledge," he answered.
Itooney's mother, however, began to observe a change
in the boy's appearance. Day by day he was afflicted
by what seemed an increasing sickness. His com
plexion became sallow, his eyes deep and sunken.
When walking the streets he would sometimes stop,
andr leaning against a post, fall into a profound slum
ber in the daytime. From a hoalthy, athletic, Greet
young man he began to show signs of a deformity.
He no longer walked erect, but stooped constantly.
He became sluggish and indolent;' his temper was
sullen and irascible.
The boy had always been industrious. His mother
had come to Schcnectady from Leadville, Colorado,
in August, 1903, and sent Leo to school until he was
sixteen. While attending school he sold newspapers,
and afterward worked for a while for a clgarmaker.
He then secured employment with the General Elec
tric Company at a salary of $50 a month. The boy
had a voice of extraordinary quality and was in de
mand at local entertainments. He often earned from
$10 to $15 a week by singing.
Until the drug took hold of him he was most solici
tous about his mother and attended to all the house
hold chores. His mother was hurt and perplexed when '
the time came that he refused to carry coal from the
cellar. One day he had told her that he had given up
his position. Duriug the day he slept most of the time
and at nights stayed away. Sometimes he was absent
from his home for an entire week.
What an Investigation Showed
and the Verdict That Resulted
His distressed mother could not guess what was
wrong with the boy. His surliness and ill temper hurt
her. When he began having hallucinations, his mother
decided that something serious was the matter with
his health. The boy had delusions that black bugs
were crawling over him and that the air was full of
bugs. He skulked about the house, declaring that
policemen were after him. He saw officers watching
him from catch basins of sewers. Sometimes at night
he awoke screaming, declaring that persons intent
upon harming him were trying to get into his bed
room through the window.
In the Pall of 1913 the boy developed hallucinations
of such a violent character that 'he was sent to tho
Ellis hospital for treatment. There the physicians
discovered the cause of his trouble. He was in such
a serious condition that they did not dare stop the
administration of heroin, hut began treatment with a
reduction in doses. In about two weeks the boy
seemed well on the road to recovery and was soou
I?Bjj
C. B. Skinner, the Druggist, Who
Must Pay Damages to Young
Rooney's Mother for Debauch
ing Her Son with Drugs.
released as practically cured. The physicians who
had treated hiru, however, discovered Immediately
after his discharge that a bottle containing several
hundred heroin pills was missing.
About this time Dr. B. R. Klrschberg, city chemist,
accompanied by the District Attorney, made a can
vass of the drug stoves in Amsterdam. Complaints
had been made that drugs were being sold to Schenec
tady boys and suspicion attached to the druggists in
the nearby village. They called upon Skinner, among
other druggists, and cross-questioned him regarding
the sale of the drug.
Skinner discreetly admitted that he had sold some
heroin tablets, but had not done so for a long time.
According to Leo Rooney's story, told recently In
court, he went to Skinner shortly after the investiga
tion made by the District Attorney and the City
Chemist to purchaso tablets and -was cautioned by
Skinner not to tell anyone where he was securing the
drug, as it "might cause trouble."
Young Rooney was often desperate In his craving
for the poison. His manner of living had completely
changed. He became a corner loafer and was ar
rested on this charge.
His mother asserted he began stealing In order to
secure money to buy heroin, that he took rugs and
carpet9 from the floor of her home, which he sold,
and that he pawned her silverware and his brother's
Clothing and even sold his own clothing. He begged
money from whomever he could. Among the ac
quaintances of Mrs. Rooney was Attorney James J.
Barry, of Schenectady, who lator handled her enso
as counsel and to whom Is due the credit of securing
the verdict against the druggists.
Leo went often into Barry's office to beg money.
Usually he asked for a quarter or half a dollar, mak
ing various excuses. He wanted to get his laundry, buy
something to eat, or purchase needed clothing. One
day he asked Barry for a dollar. Barry had observed
an amazing change In the boy's appearanco and had
become suspicious. Barry asked what Leo wanted to
use the dollar for, and Anally the boy admitted that he
wanted to get medicine which he purchased In Am
sterdam. Barry carefully undertook a rigid cross-ex
amination, and the boy, hard pressed, admitted the na
ture of the drug of which he had become a- victim*
            </text>
    </result>
        <result>
	      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045211/1916-09-08/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	      <rel>1</rel>
	      <text>
        'DOPE FIENDS'
USE DOCTORS
TO GET DRUGS
Handful of Unscrupulous
Physicians Evades Fed
eral Statute
DRUGGISTS BREAK LAW
Peddlers Supplied by Smuggling
Syndicate Sell 'Goods' on
the Streets
ARTICLE IV
The preceding article on the menacing
tprtad of the narcotic drug" evil have dealt
ivUh Ut general effect!, the crippling of the
Harrison net by court decltlom, the emug
gltng o "dope" In greet Quantifies info the
city by a criminal syndicate and the degra
dation of young men and women by Ten
derloin dwellers co-optratlng with this vn
dlcate. Today' article reveals the danger
from untcrtipulons doctors and show n
need of more drastio regulation of drug
dispensing. The inquiry by the livening
Ledger was, undertaken at the request of
Dr. Horatio O. Wood, Jr., and with the ac
tive co-operation of United Btatet District
Attorney Kane's ofIce.
By HENRY JAMES BUXTON
When the Coroner of Philadelphia looked
Into the facts attending the death ot a
youth named Tony riova, less than a week
ago, ha was led to exclaim that if no other
remedy for the cancer called 'The Arsenal
could be found It should be burned down.
From Uie little Tenth street pie shop, two
or threV blocks north of Market, the boy
had been carried suffering from the effects
of heroin. He died In a hospital a few
hours later.
A special policeman calmly observed at
the Inquest that "dope parties" were fre
quently held. In "The Arsenal" and that in
a recent raid twenty-nine persons were re
moved from tho place, all but two under
the influence of narcotic drugs.
' In cases like these the hand ot the "dope
syndicate" la clearly seen. Through an
.Intricate smuggling system It Imports Into
this city many 'rmndrod pounds of mor
phine, cocaine and heroin monthly and dis
tributes them through Tenderloin agents
and even from autos that pass through
various sections on schedule time: This syn
dicate was facing extinction under the Har
rison act, which forbids the sale of "dope"
'except on a -physician's prescription. It
gained a new lease qf life through the re-
.cent' decision, invalidating 'section 8 ,of.C&
act. for this, prevents the conviction, of those
found with the drug In their possession,.
declaring that the mere possession of largs
quantities of a drug is not evidence pre
sumptive of guilt. -
HOW 120 "FIENDS" GOT DRUGS
Legislation is required to stop this enor
mous leak In the wall raised against the
flood ot evil sustenance for crime and
degradation. But tt-'moro difficult problem
presents Itself In the evading of the law
by unscrupulous physicians.
' Dr. Frank M. Hendrlck, a negro physi
cian, of 1912 Dickinson street, was arrested
qn' A'ugust 8 by Deputy Internal Revenue
Collector McDevltt, accused of supplying
120 young "dope fiends" of South Phila
delphia with heroin, the most vicious of
modern habit-forming drugs. McDevltt and
Glovanl, a detective In the employ of ths
State Pharmaceutical Department, testified
that Doctor Hendrlck wrote heroin pre
scrlptlons for tha drug addicts under ths
pretense that, he was attempting to curs
them by the ''reduction method."
During seventy-eight days Hendrlck
wrote 1000 such prescriptions, and tor each,
one he obtained a tee of $1, making a total
of 11000 In a little more than two months.
The prescriptions were filled by two drug
gists, Samuel H. Toplan and Solomon Bay
llnson. These two druggists were also
placed under arrest, accused of having
made illicit sales to drug victims.
Tbplan and Bayllnson received 81 each
for the prescriptions tor heroin filled by
them. That -makes a grand total ot $2009
paid by the group ot 120 for their supply
during seventy-eight days. McDevltt testi
fied that the addicts who patronized Doctor
Hendrlck and the druggists ranged in ag
from sixteen to twenty-Ova years. One of
them was an eighteen-year-old boy, a high
school graduate, who was employed In ths
plant ot tbe Remington Arms Company at
116.60 a week. This boy waa giving $14 of'
his salary eaclweek to Doctor Hendrlck
and the two druggists to fe "cured" of the
heroin habit.
A mother In South Philadelphia told Mc
Devltt that her ' boy had become useless
sines he acquired vtho heroin bablt He,
too, went to Doctor Hendrlck.
OETTINO THE EVIDENCE
Glylng a fictitious nams and address,
Glovanl called on Hendrlck, and -asked hiss
to write him a prescription for 10 grain ot
heroin. Doctor Hendrlck asked how long
he used the drug. ''Six months," was ths
reply. Ths physician asksd If he desired
to be cured.
            </text>
    </result>
        <result>
	      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030214/1919-04-06/ed-1/seq-70/</id>
	      <rel>1</rel>
	      <text>
        By George S. Edgecombe
HETHER prohibition will or will
not result in a great increase
in th'e use of habit forming
drugs i*? a question on which
even the experts in drug traffic do not agree.
One of the arguments of thos*e who believe
j' will not is that one of the causes of
drug using is the relief which it affords to
persons sutTering from the effects of over
?ndu.Kt-nce in alcohol. While the experts
are debating the outcome the public gener?
ally realizes, in an indifferent way, that
ilruj; ad'licts are increasing alarmingly every
.'?car. It does not, however, realize that
??'.'.? York state now lias a new "Narcotic
ch went into effect. March 1,
and which most experts believe will cope
with the evil, present and future, better
than any statute heretofore enacted iri any
- of the Union.
Under this new law the Department of
Xarcotic Drug Control, headed by Com?
missioner Frank Richardson at Albany, di?
vides the state into four administration dis?
tricts. All persons or corporations hand
ling cocaine or opium or their derivatives
must register with this board. The manu?
facturers and wholesalers, down through
the druggists and physicians, must file one
of triplicate order blanks, giving dates and
?g the amount of drugs purchased,
prescribed or ?licensed by them. Even den
' and hospitals are included in the law.
Violation of the law is a miiukmeanor and
of th'- penalties i:; the revocation of
"ties.
The Federa! Harri on law and the original
Boytan state lav/, enacted in 19! 1, although
ded to curb the evil, had the unex
?! effect of causing physician i to fight
? t treating drug addict?. The result
was 'hat the traffic was drrven into the.
the underworld venders again.
? '? ged the various hoi pita!? and
tation houne** were crowd? ?1 with
i pplieants for reh.'f. Thia went on until
1917, when the Whitney bill went into effect.
'I htt nnw law encouraged the treatment of
xid/Os by physicians. This brought about
mi u
irinclpled physicians took advantage
Of tO d pt ? ?-?ry.t: tin:,: ., "rf..
pestera' in their office?, and thus reaped
unconscionable profit-. That abuse of their
power* became no great that Federal au
tnorii ? recently obliged to ."?* over
ific beads of otate ai police to
tari many ??tabliehmente which .were ?ell
W
ing to long lines of supposed addicts in
waiting, who in turn were selling the drug
to soldier:, -.viso' carried it right into the
military cantonments themselves.
It Hinges on
The Physician
For the past two years the problem of
drug control has centred on the physi?
cians. Justice Cornelius F. Collins, of Spe?
cial Sessions, chairman of the consolidated
committee on the drug evil, however, is
authority for the statement that not more
than 100 physicians, out of several thou
i sand in greater New York, have been "un?
conscionable" violators of the law.
Th? details of how the new law enables
the Department of Narcotic Drug Control
to keep tabs on a given quantity of opium,
morphine, cocaine or heroin as it passes
from manufacturer to the ultimate con?
sumer are too many and devious for the
purposes of this article. The supporters
of the bill admit that under existing condi?
tions of imperfect national and interna?
tional control it is at best imperfect, but
they believe that it is a forward step in
the solution of the difficulty.
Dr. James A. Hamilton, Commissioner of
Correction, says the new law will not pre?
vent physicians from issuing several pre?
scriptions to the same addict or patient in
one day. Supporters of the bill point out
that the Department of Drug Control un?
der the law has means at hand to discover
that abuse, and when discovered it, is ex?
tremely likely that the offending physician
will lose his license to obtain the drug.
Ore of the grounds for anticipating a
f great increase in drug addicts is the war.
| Morphine and, in many cases, heroin have
] been largely used in surgical cases where
soldiers have been gassed. It is feared that
I sufficient quantities have been absorbed in
i this manner to form habits among many of
! the returning troops. The War Department
is trying to guard against this by careful
medical examination at discharge of troops,
and embryo addicts will be treated in gov?
ernment hospitals.
The Number
Of Addicts
The number of addicts in New York City
has been conservatively estimated by Jus?
tice Collins at 1 per cent of the population,
or about 100,000. Causes of acquired habits
are mainly these: Extensive surgical treat
! ment, protracted medication for bodily ail?
ments and disease, persistent taking of
patent medicines containing an appreciable
quantity of the drug, seceking relief from
alcoholic excesses, to association, environ?
ment, gang influence and foolish curiosity,
! and last, but not least, to the interchange
of the drug in jails and prisons, where it is
i indulged in furiously by felons in a frenzied
attempt to overcome mental anguish.
The addicts are found in all walks of life,
the rich and the poor; all professions and
business callings. The use of the drug by
the "underworld" and criminal classes ren?
ders more sinister their power and greatly
I hampers their chances for reform.
Opium using and morphine taking seem
to be waning. Cocaine, and particularly
! heroin, are most, in demand. The hero
' in habit is growing at an appalling rate
' and strikes particularly at the youth of
1 America. Between the ages of seventeen
- and twenty-two there are so many heroin
i users that the average age of its victims
is easily set at twenty years.
All drug control experts recognize the
necessity of treatment of addicts by gradual
withdrawal. There, is, however, no known
specific remedy for the cure of drug addic?
tion. In fact, the whole tr
?s at seh on the subject, so much so, that
Health Commissioner Dr. Royal S. Cope
land has just announced that the Health
Department of New York will conduct a re?
search into the subject among the patients
on North Brother Island. The cocaine user
is the more susceptible to treatment.
Perils After
A Cure
Temporary cure of all narcotic addict? is
not so difficult. It is the exercise of the
free will of the patient after he is dis?
charged that cannot be. controlled. A period
of convalescence and recupera: ion is abso?
lutely necessary. Plenty of fresh air an?
proper physical exercise while the patient
is under careful surveillance are most df
" sirable. The Warwick and Harts Island
farms are to be thrown open soon for tin?
purpose.
It is generally agreed that no permanent
' or adequate relief from the growing druf
i evil will be had until tne attempt ?i 'V'rt
! national control, interrupted by the war in
1914, is resumed. Conditions in the Phil
; ippines in 1909 compelled the United States
i to take the initiative in this international
consideration of the evil. -Shutting off ?'
the opium traffic with China served onlv to
stimulate the morphine and cocaine bvr
] ness, with a consequent loss of $l0o.00i.
S 000 aggregate annual opium revenue to th?
great nations which had voluntarily sncr1'
, (iced the traffic only to see their subjects
? pressing two other deadly druir? int? th*
hands of the Far Eastern people who h?d
; heroically determined to abandon W*
[ "opium vice.'* l
            </text>
    </result>
        <result>
	      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85058396/1919-04-28/ed-1/seq-4/</id>
	      <rel>0</rel>
    </result>
    <result>
	      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84026749/1922-03-19/ed-1/seq-44/</id>
	      <rel>0</rel>
    </result>
  </results>
</topic>
</topics>


<topics>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-maria-tallchief/selected-articles</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn88063294/1944-10-11/ed-1/seq-14/</id>
	      <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
            <result>
	      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045462/1951-02-04/ed-1/seq-107/</id>
	      <rel>1</rel>
	      <text>
          If Maria Tailchiers Osage
great-grandfather could see
her now, he’d yell “How?”
Color Photo by- John Rusitrll
is is probably impossible to
ance,” said the ballet master
during a rehearsal. “Maria,” he called
to a dark young ballerina, “you do it!”
And Maria did. In London, New York
and U.S. cities from coast to coast,
audiences have come to know that
Maria Tallchief accomplishes the im
possible with incredible ease. She is
recognized as the most exciting of Amer
ica’s young home-grown ballerinas.
When the curtain went up over a
year ago on a new version of an old
ballet, “Firebird,” no one was prepared
for the electrifying effect Maria Tall
chief generated from the Stravinsky
music. As the bird, she was truly a flam
ing figure — she soared through the air
in effortless flight, she preened, she
shimmered, she gloried in speed and
airy freedom. Then, captured by the
prince, she wrestled to regain that free
dom by soft and feminine wiles.
When the curtain descended to
storms of applause, Maria was no
longer merely the New York City
Ballet’s prize package but the equal of
such top U.S. dancers as Nora Kaye
and Rosella Hightower. With them, she
proves that an American ballerina is a
match for any in the world.
In Maria one sees not just the results
of exhaustive schooling in technique
and tradition of the ballet. She has
movements as broad and free as the
land which gave her birth; an athletic
prowess that is the heritage of almost
every American girl or boy and a proud
bearing which is perhaps a bequest
from her noble Indian forebears.
For Maria, dark-haired and deli
cately bronzed, was born on an Osage
reservation in Oklahoma, daughter of
an Indian father and a Scottish mother,
HOME-GROWN ballerina: Maria Tallchief specializes in the impossible
granddaughter of Eliza Tall Chief,
great - granddaughter of Chief Big
Heart. Drums and tribal dancing are
dim memories. She recalls more vividly
that at five she wore toe slippers and,
holding a flag aloft, spun endlessly to
"The Stars and Stripes Forever.”
Maria’s sister, Marjorie, is a balle
rina also and a potential rival. Neither
takes the rivalry seriously. They have
inherited a sense of humor from their
father, who once told them, spoofing
the myth that all Osages are oil-rich:
“My daughters, I am proud of you.
You are the first Osages in generations
to work for a living.”
        </text>
      </result>
            <result>
	      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045462/1951-12-09/ed-1/seq-171/</id>
	      <rel>1</rel>
	      <text>
The New York City Ballet Company has added a
strip tease to its repertory this year. The ballet, a
frothy, comic bit based on the eternal-triangle theme,
is called "A La Francaix” (Jean Francaix is the
composer^. It made its debut this year with Prima
Ballerina Maria Tallchief as the bewitching stripper.
        </text>
      </result>
            <result>
	      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045462/1953-02-04/ed-1/seq-20/</id>
	      <rel>1</rel>
	      <text>
        Maria Tallchief gave this correspondent a dancing lesson
yesterday and that is as nice a thing as is likely to happen to a man.
Lest any one leap to a false conclusion, it was a lesson “about”
ballet, and ballerinas: not “in” ballet.
The New York City Ballet with which she will be dancing
three concerts here February 14-16, Inclusive, at Constitution Hall,
let Miss Tallchief off from re-'
hearsal yesterday. She was free
for the whole day with nothing to
do but get up at 6 a.m., fly to
Washington, and spend the
whole day talking to the press
and making radio and television
appearances.
Miss Tallchief likes this mis
sionary work, although probably
not as much as she likes “Swan
Lake.” and she is both gracious
and competent at it. When and
if she decides to hang up her
ballet slippers—a thought that
has never entered her classic
head—she would make a great
advance agent, although there
would no doubt be union prob
lems. As a union philosopher
once said to us. “there are al
ways union problems.”
** * *
Miss Tallchief eats sweet rolls
and butter, with coffee, for
breakfast. This gives her enough
energy to cover more conversa
tional ground than any one you
are likely to meet at a morning
meal, except of course the person
you are married to.
A few of the things this break
fast covered verbally included a :
great ballerina’s preferences
(somel between classic and new j
ballets; the satisfaction of danc
ing in a musical or revue (why
not?) as compared with concert
repertory; dancing in the movies
(it pays well and dancers always
need money); where is Nana
Gollner (California) now. and
what a charming person is Mar
got Fonteyn of the Sadler’s Wells
ballet. And, oh, yes, television
(interesting).
Breakfast with Miss Tallchief,
as any one can see, is far rangier j
th&n usual.
** * *
The Oklahoma girl, who is
regarded by many as America’s
finest ballerina, is married, but ;
not to a fellow professional. Her j
husband is an -airlines pilot
whose taste in dancing, she says
with a laugh, “is good because it
agrees with mine. After all isn’t
that a workable standard of
taste?” During the war, her fly
ing husband was a Marine, not
a pilot but a gunner. Miss Tall
chief pantomimes this by firing
a gun in the fashion es a Hop
along Cassidy fan. This, because i
it is a dancer's way of talking?
Not at all, she says. It's a flyer’s
way.
“Tie their hands behind them
and they couldn’t talk at all,”
she says.
Miss Tallchief, who keeps busy
50 or 51 weeks a year because
this is away to have a happy life
as an artist and a human, is not
at all puzzled by the great popu
larity of the ballet during the
last decade.
"It is the blending of all the
arts,” she says. “It combines
music, drama, painting with a
kind of irresistible eloquence
and beauty.” Its popularity, she
should think, is inevitable and
bound to increase. The movies
and television will be influential
in this direction and she is in- j
terested in both.
She enjoyed herself playing the
role of Anna Pevlowa in MGM’s
recent Esther Williams’spectacle,
“Million Dollar Mermaid.” More
over, in the fashion of a keenly
observant artist, she learned a
lot.
“I was told.” she says, “that
here was the form in which the
artist had the complete chance
for perfection—that he could
sort of dance a step, stop if it
were unsatisfactory, and then do
 it all over again. But I learned,
1 Instead, that my part of the film
was to be shot In a single day. I
think I never worked a harder
day in my life.”
Happily, she likes hard work
and challenging assignments.
She, as a modest girl only could
be, is flattered that the studio
asked her in view of the fact
that it has such dancers on its
roster as Moira Shearer, Leslie
Caron and Cyd Charisse.
** * *
Its trip here, and to Baltimore,
is the New York City Ballet’s
first tour in this country but it
has been abroad where it is
hailed as America’s finest dance
company.
Miss Tallchief is happy with
all but one attitude of European
critics toward the George Ba
lanchine troupe. This ia their
reference to the company’s “ath
leticism.” a rather silly word
which Miss Tallchief thinks may
grow out of the fact that “we
have neither much scenery nor
lavish costuming.”
These, she is confident will be
taken care of. along with refer
i ences to “athleticism,” when
! the company is as rich financially
as it is blessed artistically.
        </text>
      </result>
            <result>
	      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045462/1953-08-23/ed-1/seq-69/</id>
	      <rel>1</rel>
	      <text>
        Maria Tall
chief, ballerina of the New York
City Ballet, is considered one of
the premier ballerinas in the
United States and the fact that
her father is an Osage Indian
even more makes her 100 per
cent American.
When Miss Tallchief danced
;in Hollywood recently at the
Greek Theater, many of her for
mer classmates from Beverly
Hills High School were there to
cheer her.
Maria studied with Mr. Ble
cher, Marge Champion’s father,
and with Mme. Nijinsky. In
her early teens she danced with
the ballet company of the Los
Angeles Light Opera. Though
Maria gave early signs of out
standing talent, she has climbed j
higher than was anticipated.
When I lunched with Maria j
recently at the Beverly Hills;
Country Club I found her ac- !
cepting her fame with the mod
esty associated with those who
know they have reached the top.
Wearing a simple black dress,
high heels and her hair drawn j
back in a pony tail, she was not |
recognized by any of her fans.
We chatted about this and j
Maria remarked how removed a j
ballerina's life was from her fans.
“The ballet.” she commented, j
, “is the most demanding and the
least commercial of any of the j
performing arts. Even an opera
singer can reach a larger public
through her records.”
I wanted to know what Miss
Tallchief felt had helped her
| most in her climb to the top.
“Work.” Maria said emphati
cally. “If you want to be a
! ballerina you must devote all
your energy to the dance. You
| must love it because you don’t
For Beauty Parade
Send a stamped, self-ad
dressed envelope and 5
cents for each of the fol
lowing leaflets. Order them
by number:
M-38—Olivia de Havil
land’s Routine for Releasing
Nervous Tension.
M-40 —Irene Dunne’s Ex
ercises for Flexibility.
M-41 Anne Baxter’s
Complexion cures.
Mail requests to Lydia
Lane, Mirror Syndicate, 145
South Spring street, Los
Angeles 53. Calif. DO NOT
write The Star.
get a lot of worldly goods. The
satisfaction comes from within.
“You must be a perfectionist,”
Maria continued, “and you must
look ahead to find ways to im
prove yourself. It is very im
portant never to become satis
fied. Constructive criticism is
very helpful but, unfortunately,
j there is , too little of it.”
“You’ve mentioned nothing
about appearance,” I commented.
“A ballet dancer is judged by
her talent more than by any
thing else, but when she is on
| the stage she has an obligation
to be a perfectionist in her
grooming. I always go to the
' theatre at least two hours early
j in order to do my hair, my make
up, and to clean my ballet slip
j pers and tights.”
i I asked Maria to tell me one
a
Jjppp
. v !( HmyK" m r
JSRpv ' j, IraS e s' lßgtß || H fKB I
SHE'S ON HER TOES—Maria Tallchief, star of the famed
New York City BaHet company now touring the United
States, tells Lydia Lane her exercise routine.
of the most important obstacles
she's had to overcome.
“I have to fight becoming too
absorbed in my career. I devote
so much of myself to dancing
that sometimes I lose my sense
of perspective. It is not easy
for me to have outside interests.”
‘‘Do you have any?” I asked.
‘‘When I am not on the road
I make all my own clothes. I
enjoy designing and the very act
of sewing is a form of relaxa
tion.”
‘‘What do you do to relax phy
sically?”
Maria laughed. ‘‘Every dancer
puts her feet up on the first
thing she can find. And on the
days we have a matinee I soak
my feet. I sit on the side of a
tub and use first hot water and
then cold. Alternating the tem
perature brings up the circula
tion and gives immediate relief.”
‘‘Do you have trouble falling
asleep?” I wanted to know.
‘‘l like to read before I turn
out the light.”
I asked if Miss Tallchief had
ever had a weight problem.
“Not when I am working be
cause I eat lots of meat. At
four o'clock I usually have a
pound of steak and a green salad,
and after the ballet I like a
steak sandwich.”
I wanted to know what she
considered her top beauty sec
ret.
“Exercise.” Maria said quickly.
“I recommend ballet training
even if you don’t intend to
dance. It improves your health,
j your posture and is something
! you can use all your life. Once
you are used to exercising your
muscles you don’t feel comfort
able without it.”
I asked Maria to tell me some
of her favorite exercises.
“For legs and thighs, hold
onto a chair for balance, stand
with your feet apart, toes out,”
she explained. “Bend your knees
I until you are in a squatting po
sition. Keep your back straight
and your heels on the floor as
long as you comfortably can.
You should feel a pull in the
back of your legs which will keep
| your muscles firm and prevent
your losing the spring in your
! step.
“Do you have a good waist
and stomach exercise?” I want
ed to know.
“With your feet apart, hold
i a heavy book in your hands and
! extend your arms above your
head,” Maria said. “Bend as far
1 as you can first to one side and
then the other. It’* simple, but
the results this exercise brings
are wonderful.
! “Then, in the same position
of feet apart, book in your
hands, extend your arms high
above your head,” Maria added.
“Bring your head down between
your legs, touching the book to
the floor. Come back to the first
position and bend back as far
as you can. For best results, this
exercise should be done rhyth
mically.”
        </text>
      </result>
            <result>
	      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045462/1954-09-22/ed-1/seq-57/</id>
	      <rel>1</rel>
	      <text>
Maria Talfchief Gets
Divorce In Jaurez
BV the Associated Press
EL PASO, Tex., Sept. 22.
Maria Tallchief, prima ballerina
of the Ballet Russe de Monte
Carlo, called the greatest Ameri
can-born ballet star, obtained a
quickie Juarez divorce from her
second huisband, Emourza Natir
boff, last Wednesday, it was
learned yesterday.
Judge Oscar Martinez Fourzan
of the Second Civil Court said
the divorce was uncontested and
was granted by mutual consent
of both parties.
The 29-year-old ballerina
formerly was a star of the New
York City Center Ballet and
recently joined the Ballet Russe.
        </text>
      </result>
            <result>
	      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045462/1956-02-12/ed-1/seq-14/</id>
	      <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
            <result>
	      <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-maria-tallchief/selected-articles</id>
	      <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
  </results>
</topic>
</topics>

<topics>
  <topic>
    <id>hhttps://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/search/pages/results/?state=&date1=1756&date2=1963&proxtext=about+pearl+harbor&x=0&y=0&dateFilterType=yearRange&rows=20&searchType=basic</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045462/1946-12-01/ed-1/seq-115/#date1=1756&index=0&rows=20&words=about+Harbor+Pearl&searchType=basic&sequence=0&state=&date2=1963&proxtext=about+pearl+harbor&y=0&x=0&dateFilterType=yearRange&page=1</id>
	      <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
      <result>
	      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045462/1942-03-08/ed-1/seq-83/#date1=1756&index=1&rows=20&words=about+Harbor+Pearl&searchType=basic&sequence=0&state=&date2=1963&proxtext=about+pearl+harbor&y=0&x=0&dateFilterType=yearRange&page=1</id>
	      <rel>1</rel>
	      <text>
        There is one painful truth about Pearl Harbor that
we must remember.
That is the manifest fact that when those enemy
bombers swooped down from the skies, their pilots
knew the exact location of every strategic objective
on the island.
Maps in their cockpits — painstakingly prepared
months before in Tokio — pointed the way accurately
to hangars and storage facilities of Hickam Field; to
soldiers’ barracks, gasoline dumps, ship anchorages and
ground fortifications. Low-flying fighters knew exactly
which roads to strafe to prevent the defenders from
reaching their posts or taking the air against them.
Pearl Harbor held no secrets for the invader!
Sadly enough, this same fact was true of the Philip
pines; is true of Alaska, and the Canal Zone. It is true,
also, of every vital defense point in the continental United
States.
For years Japan has been building up this fund of
strategic information with little hindrance from us. Its
“fishing fleets,” commanded by disguised naval officers,
have taken harbor soundings and have studied our
coast defenses, our dock facilities, our ship movements
along the entire Pacific coast.
Japanese “students” at American universities were
actually military officers —and spent their holidays
photographing the charming views afforded by our
bridges, our water-supply systems and our dams.
Japanese naval and aeronautical engineers attended
our finest technical schools and visited every near-by
aircraft factory and important industrial plant.
Japanese army officers were even permitted three
to nine months of training at our Army posts.
And always supplementing this direct research by
military men were the reports of hundreds of commer
cial representatives of Mitsui & Company and the other
huge business concerns of Japan and of so-called Japa
nese tourists.
For years the general staffs of the world’s armies have
been tirelessly engaged in "spotting” military objec
tives in possible enemy countries. Those efforts were
not limited to trying to ferret out secrets of new guns
and bombsights, warships and planes. It is just as vital
to know the location of water supplies, communication
and transportation networks, airports, gasoline storage
points, naval bases and warehouses.
         </text>
      </result>
      <result>
	      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84020662/1945-11-09/ed-1/seq-1/#date1=1756&index=2&rows=20&words=about+About+Harbor+Pearl&searchType=basic&sequence=0&state=&date2=1963&proxtext=about+pearl+harbor&y=0&x=0&dateFilterType=yearRange&page=1</id>
	      <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
      <result>
	      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045462/1947-05-21/ed-1/seq-7/#date1=1756&index=4&rows=20&words=about+ABOUT+HARBOR+Harbor+Pearl+PEARL&searchType=basic&sequence=0&state=&date2=1963&proxtext=about+pearl+harbor&y=0&x=0&dateFilterType=yearRange&page=1</id>
	      <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
      <result>
	      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn88063294/1942-12-06/ed-1/seq-1/#date1=1756&index=5&rows=20&words=about+Harbor+Pearl&searchType=basic&sequence=0&state=&date2=1963&proxtext=about+pearl+harbor&y=0&x=0&dateFilterType=yearRange&page=1</id>
	      <rel>1</rel>
	      <text>
        Army and navy personnel losses in the Pearl
Harbor battle totaled 4,575 men killed, w*ounded or
missing. Of these, 2,343 were killed outright or died
of wounds.
Here is the navy's official list of American war
ship casualties:
Sunk or damaged:
The 19.700-ton battleship Arizona (total loss).
The 29,000-ton battleship Oklahoma.
The 32,000-ton battleship C alifornia.
The 29,000-ton battleship Nevada.
The 31,800-ton battleship West Virginia.
The 1,500-ton destroyer Shaw.
         </text>
      </result>
      <result>
	      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn89060186/1942-10-16/ed-1/seq-4/#date1=1756&index=6&rows=20&words=about+Harbor+Pearl&searchType=basic&sequence=0&state=&date2=1963&proxtext=about+pearl+harbor&y=0&x=0&dateFilterType=yearRange&page=1</id>
	      <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
      <result>
	      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84037526/1953-10-21/ed-1/seq-1/#date1=1756&index=7&rows=20&words=about+Harbor+Pearl&searchType=basic&sequence=0&state=&date2=1963&proxtext=about+pearl+harbor&y=0&x=0&dateFilterType=yearRange&page=1</id>
	      <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
      <result>
	      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn89070012/1945-12-13/ed-1/seq-6/#date1=1756&index=8&rows=20&words=about+Harbor+Pearl&searchType=basic&sequence=0&state=&date2=1963&proxtext=about+pearl+harbor&y=0&x=0&dateFilterType=yearRange&page=1</id>
	      <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
      <result>
	      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn94050056/1909-09-25/ed-1/seq-3/#date1=1756&index=9&rows=20&words=about+Harbor+Pearl&searchType=basic&sequence=0&state=&date2=1963&proxtext=about+pearl+harbor&y=0&x=0&dateFilterType=yearRange&page=1</id>
	      <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
      <result>
	      <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/2017236974/1946-01-10/ed-1/seq-6/#date1=1756&index=11&rows=20&words=about+Harbor+Pearl&searchType=basic&sequence=0&state=&date2=1963&proxtext=about+pearl+harbor&y=0&x=0&dateFilterType=yearRange&page=1</id>
	      <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
      </results>
</topic>
</topics>
